<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The controversie about infants church-membership and baptism, epitomized in two treatises the first, shewing the certainty of the salvation of all dying infants, against the doctrine of the Pædo-baptists, who deny salvation to all infants that die unbaptized, either directly, or by the natural consequence of their arguments : the second, being a plain confutation of Mr. J.B. his second book of more than 60 queries, about infants church-membership and baptism, by a proportionable number of antiqueries : being an essay towards a more Christian accomodation between the Pædo-baptists, and the baptized believers, published for that happy end / by Thomas Grantham.</title>
            <author>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1529</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18409246</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18409246</idno>
            <idno type="VID">206466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23662)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1634:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The controversie about infants church-membership and baptism, epitomized in two treatises the first, shewing the certainty of the salvation of all dying infants, against the doctrine of the Pædo-baptists, who deny salvation to all infants that die unbaptized, either directly, or by the natural consequence of their arguments : the second, being a plain confutation of Mr. J.B. his second book of more than 60 queries, about infants church-membership and baptism, by a proportionable number of antiqueries : being an essay towards a more Christian accomodation between the Pædo-baptists, and the baptized believers, published for that happy end / by Thomas Grantham.</title>
                  <author>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692.</author>
                  <author>Grantham, Thomas, 1634-1692. Querist examined.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Part II has special t.p. with title and imprint: The querist examined. The second part / by Thomas Grantham. [S.l. : s.n.], 1679.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and slightly faded, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barret, John, 1631-1713.</term>
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE CONTROVERSIE ABOUT Infants Church-Memberſhip and BAPTISM, Epitomized.</p>
            <p>In two TREATISES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Firſt,</hi> Shewing the certainty of the Salvation of all Dying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, againſt the Doctrine of the <hi>Paedo-Baptiſts,</hi> who deny Salvation to all Infants that die Unbaptized, either directly, or by the natural Conſequence of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second,</hi> Being a plain Confutation of Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> his ſecond Book of more than 60 Queries, about Infants Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip and Baptiſm, by a proportionable number of Antiqueries.</p>
            <p>Being an Eſſay towards a more Chriſtian Accommodation between the Paedo-Baptiſts, and the Baptized Believers. Publiſhed for that happy end.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS GRANTHAM,</hi> Author of <hi>The Queriſt Examined:</hi> wherein Fifty Queries gathered and propounded by the ſaid <hi>J. B.</hi> are Redargued.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us (in his <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> p. 179. 3<hi>d Edit.) That in the Primitive Times, none were Baptized without an expreſs Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, wherein they renounced the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, and engaged themſelves to Chriſt, and promiſed to obey Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206466:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:206466:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> J. B. <hi>Collector of the Queries,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Shall here requite your Thanks you gave me in your laſt, by returning Thanks to you for your endeavours for Peace among differing Chriſtians, and particularly for the terms propounded for an Accommodation; and I find the ſame delivered lately by Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, for which I return him thanks alſo; For methinks there wants but a little more than is offered towards the obtaining ſo much Union between the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> and <hi>Paedo-Baptiſts,</hi> as might make them a great Bleſſing one to another.</p>
            <p>But Sir, now give me leave to blame you (and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> alſo) for miſrepreſenting your Friends, the Baptized Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: Whilſt you in your Epiſtle, and he in his Books, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent us to the World, as a People who <hi>exclude Infants from Goſpel Grace;</hi> deny them to be <hi>capable of Pardon by a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Covenant;</hi> as if we <hi>left all Infants in the Kingdom of the Devil, took away all Comfort from Parents concerning their dying Infants.</hi> When yet it is moſt certain, all theſe things are utterly untrue; and it is alſo certain, that our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine concerning dying Infants, is far more comfortable than yours, as I am perſuaded will appear to ſuch as read the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſes.</p>
            <p>And I am alſo perſuaded, could there be once a free and friendly Debate between the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> and <hi>Pedo Baptiſts,</hi> about Infants intereſt in the Covenant of Grace, and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of their Salvation by Chriſt; without incumbring that Diſcourſe with Baptiſm, it were eaſie to compoſe their Difference in that Point. Which done, it's hoped might be no impoſſible thing to accommodate their difference in the caſe of Baptiſm it ſelf. But whilſt theſe two things are confounded, Diſputes are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206466:3"/> Perplexed, in ſo much as that a right underſtanding can hardly be attained on either ſide. Nor do many Readers underſtand what Mr. <hi>B.</hi> means, when he would have Infants <hi>admitted</hi> Members of the Viſible Church by the <hi>Law of Infants Church-Memberſhip unrepealed,</hi> any more than they know what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended on Mr. <hi>T's.</hi> part, by their being taken to be Members by <hi>a Tranſient Fact;</hi> both paſſages being too occult for every Reader.</p>
            <p>Sir, let me ſay this farther, Could but the Reformed Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans once get over this stumbling-block of Paedo-Rantiſm, and reſolve upon the way of Believers Baptiſm, which is ſo perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous in the Scripture, and in the mean time take the most ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn way (which might be warrantable) to dedicate their Infants to God in the Name of Christ; It would certainly prove the best Expedient to bring down the Papal Confidence: for as they know (and acknowledg) that uſage to stand upon the authority of Tradition, and not upon the Scripture War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſo they glory over the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> for his Inconstancy, in denying unwritten Tradition, and yet their very Baptiſm hath no other Foundation: But were the Doctrine of Baptiſm pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from this Leven, and restored to its Primitive Purity, it would find all the Univerſities of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as much buſineſs to defend their Infant Sprinkling, as ever they were at to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Tranſubstantiation.</p>
            <p>What you write concerning my <hi>Queriſt Examined,</hi> I ſhall take little Notice of, eſpecially for that I find it attended with overmuch Levity; and at the most is but a kind of Carping at Words, rather than a ſolid Anſwer; and there ſeems to me an unwillingneſs in you to understand what you flirt at, about the Meſſenger's Office, and about Impoſition of Hands, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Scriptureleſs Matters (as your Paedo-Rantiſm is) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires your more ſerious thoughts, whether you understand, or like my Sentiments there or not. I am your Real Friend,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. GRANTHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:206466:3"/>
                  <head>The Controverſie of Infants Church-Memberſhip, and Baptiſm Epitomized. The firſt Treatiſe ſhewing the certainty of the Salvation of all Dying Infants.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>SECTION I.</head>
                     <p>IT is evident by the Writings of many Paedo-Baptiſts, both Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Prelatiſts, and Presbyterians, that they do all either hold abſolutely that no Unbaptized Infant can be ſaved, or at leaſt that their Salvation is very doubtful. And among theſe Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and from him Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> hath not a little amuſed the Minds of Men about this Matter. Only they have uſed a more ſubtle way, coupling the Church-Memberſhip of Infants with Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, confounding thereby the Readers and themſelves too, they not being able to ſay which hath the Precedency: for if Infants be Church-Members without, or before they be Baptized; let them ſay ſo, and let them prove it well, I ſhall be glad to ſee it done. But then let them never ſay, as Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> doth, in his Epiſtle, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Books, <hi>That Infants are not ſo much as ſeemingly in a ſtate of Salvation; that Parents can have no comfort of their dying Children,</hi> Making <hi>Baptiſm</hi> the <hi>ſoveraign Antidote againſt their Griefs and Fears, when they are removed in Infancy.</hi> As will appear more fully in the Examination of the Queries in the ſecond Treatiſe.</p>
                     <p>Now this new art of pleading for Infant-Baptiſm by virtue of their Church-Memberſhip (and not from the Scriptures directly, as others have aſſayed to do, but could never perform the Task, and therefore have been forced to take ſanctuary with the Papiſts in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written Traditions, and that with ill ſucceſs) I ſay, conſidering this new Subtilty of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> I perceived the Controverſie to riſe very high, and Queſtions thereupon to be greatly multiplied, eſpecially
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206466:4"/> upon the Point of Infants <hi>Church-Memberſhip.</hi> Hereupon I thought it needful to conſider this Matter, for I perceived very good Men engaged on both ſides, and, as I conceive, much more ſtraining in the Point than needed, by which means the Reader ſhall ſooner fill his Head with amazement than ſatisfaction, in tracing the ſeveral windings of their Diſputations.</p>
                     <p>Nor do I think my ſelf wiſer than they, but having the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to ſtand and view whilſt they engage, I hope I have thereby been led to the conſideration of a Medium, which if duly conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and improved by better Pens than mine, will (I am much perſuaded) reconcile the difference about Infants viſible Church-Memberſhip. And yet I do not at all doubt, that Infant-Baptiſm will remain without any ground at all.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. II.</head>
                     <p>And this I ſhall demonſtrate, by ſhewing, <hi>That all Infants are in a viſible ſtate of Salvation, and ſo of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church of God, and cannot be put out of that bleſſed ſtate, till by their voluntary departure from God, by chooſing ſinful ways, they deſtroy themſelves.</hi> And here we will make our entrance by a paſſage out of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf, who ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>All Mankind is brought by Chriſt under a Covenant of Grace, which is not vain nor repealed by God; But as their abuſe of the Grace of the Covenant may caſt them out. For as a Covenant of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Nature was made with all Mankind in innocent</hi> Adam, <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s more Reaſons, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. 6.</note> 
                        <hi>ſo a Covenant of Grace was made with all Mankind in lapſed</hi> Adam, Gen. 3. 15. <hi>in the promiſed Seed, and renewed again with all Mankind in</hi> Noah.</p>
                     <p>Now this Doctrine being no more than plain truth, we ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to the caſe in hand, by ſhewing, Firſt, That <hi>this Covenant of Grace, was a viſible Church-Covenant.</hi> 2. <hi>That it was made with all Mankind, and takes place in their Infancy.</hi> 3. <hi>That it was never repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God.</hi> 4. That no Infant did ever abuſe the Grace of this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. And therefore, <hi>no Infant was ever caſt out of this Covenant.</hi> And then fifthly, <hi>They all ſtand viſible Members of the Catholick Church by virtue of this Covenant,</hi> however their Parents do abuſe, or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it; and hence it will follow, <hi>no dying Infant is Damned, but are all in a viſible ſtate of Salvation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:206466:4"/> 1. That this Covenant of Grace, firſt expreſſed <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. was either a Church-Covenant, or elſe there was no Church-Covenant in the World, that we read of, from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> this being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all the Covenant that is named, during theſe Times, beſides that Covenant of Intire Nature made before the Fall. And that Covenant of Nature being broken by <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him by all his Poſterity, it being not a Covenant of Grace, could not juſtifie the Offenders in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ight of God. There muſt therefore be ſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervening Act of Grace, or Mercy from God, elſe <hi>Adam</hi> (even whole Mankind who were then in his Loins) muſt have ſtood under Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for ever, ſeeing <hi>no Man could by any means redeem his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor give to God a Ranſom for him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is the received Doctrine of Chriſtians that the Viſible Church began in <hi>Adam,</hi> and that his Family was the Church, wherefore the whole World being then the Church, and that Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant being made with the whole World, that was to proceed from <hi>Adam,</hi> and this Covenant yet remaining; it follows againſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, that whole Mankind, conſidered as they come into the World in all the ſeveral Ages of it, are in a viſible ſtate of Salvation, and ſo of the Catholick Church of God.</p>
                     <p>But whereas many did Apoſtatize from the Grace of God's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, by <hi>corrupting his way,</hi> Gen. 6. 12. It was neceſſary that they ſhould be ejected, and therefore was the Covenant accommodated, and appropriated to thoſe who had not ſinned themſelves out of it; but ſtill the Innocent muſt not be ejected with the Nocent: for it is he only <hi>that ſinneth,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name ſhall be blotted out of the Book which God hath written,</hi> Gen. 32. 32, 33. And therefore neither the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod which God took with <hi>Noah,</hi> in ſettling the Covenant of his Grace, nor yet that Order which he obſerved with <hi>Abraham,</hi> was excluſive of any Infant in the World, as to the Grace of God in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Eternal Life, no more than the eſtabliſhment of it by Chriſt in the Goſpel, in a far more excellent order for diſtinguiſhing the Precious from the Vile, is in any wiſe excluſive of any dying Infant; for <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Nor can any Man ſhew either by Scripture or Reaſon, that God will ſhut out all the dying Infants of wicked Men, from Life and Salvation by Chriſt, no nor ſo much as any one of them; for we are ſure that <hi>the Judgment of God is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to truth, that the Judge of all the Earth will do right.</hi> That the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206466:5"/> Condemned ſhall <hi>be judged according to the deeds done in the Body;</hi> but alas, as for poor Infants, <hi>what have they done?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That this Covenant was made with all Mankind, is thus cleared, becauſe it was made with <hi>Adam,</hi> without the leaſt intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the excluſion of any part of his Poſterity (as they proceed from him) to the end of the World; neither hath God himſelf explained the Covenant of Grace to be Excluſive of any, but for the cauſe of their own iniquity; and this was evident firſt in the caſe of <hi>Cain,</hi> who not being faithful in his offering was not accepted. Yet God was pleaſed to ſhew him the cauſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>If thou doſt well, ſhalt thou not be accepted?</hi> It ſhould ſeem God never rejected him till this time, neither did he now delight to reject him, but graciouſly expoſtulates with <hi>Cain,</hi> to convince him of his evil, and aſſures him of acceptation <hi>if he did well.</hi> If then <hi>Cain</hi> had an intereſt in the Grace of God, who can we ſuppoſe to be ſhut out, till they with <hi>Cain</hi> ſhut themſelves out of it?</p>
                     <p>Evident it is that the Covenant of Grace extended to thoſe Rebels in the Old World, becauſe we read <hi>the long ſuffering of God waited on them,</hi> and he gave them <hi>time of Repentance,</hi> and ſent a Preacher of Righteouſneſs <hi>(even the Righteouſneſs of Faith)</hi> among them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 7. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Chriſt went by his Spirit and preached to them,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. though none of them believed his Word. Now ſuch Acts on God's part are great Evidences of his Graciouſneſs towards Men, and ſhews that he remembers his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, made in Chriſt with them, even for them that rebel againſt him, and ſo periſh. And then how ſhall we think that he ſhould not be gracious to poor Infants, who never rebelled againſt him?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>The Covenant of Grace was never repealed by God;</hi> for if it be, there is now no Covenant at all; nor can it be repealed to one Man, but it muſt be repealed to all Men. 'Tis true, Men may forfeit the Mercy held forth in that Covenant, but the Covenant cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, for then there can be no certainty of any Mercy for Sinners; Chriſt himſelf may as ſoon be made Null, as this Covenant. For what if ſome Apoſtatize, or do not believe, ſhall this make the Grace of God without effect? God forbid. When we continually ſee that Covenant of God's Grace diſplayed, making overtures of kindneſs to Sinners (even to the chief of Sinners) what ſhall we ſay, if any Infant be without a part in that Covenant? Is he not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206466:5"/> then the chief of Sinners? It is not then the Sin of Parents that can repeal the Covenant of Grace with reſpect to Infants.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>No Infants did ever abuſe the Grace of the Covenant made with them in</hi> Adam, Gen. 3. 15. <hi>therefore no Infant was caſt out of it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Although it is moſt true, that Original Sin is come upon Infants, and Death by Sin; yet this is as true, that Original Sin was not committed againſt the Covenant of Grace, and therefore Infants are not guilty of any Sin committed againſt the Covenant of Grace, and conſequently are not deprived of the benefit of it. Otherwiſe if the Sin of Subſequent Parents ſhould make void the Grace of the ſecond Covenant to their Infants, as the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi> made his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity guilty of the breach of the firſt Covenant; we may then juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cry out, <hi>Who then can be ſaved?</hi> And therefore was our Saviour <hi>the Mediator of the New Teſtament, for the Redemption of the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that were under the firſt Teſtament,</hi> Heb. 9. 15. Wherefore ſeeing Infants ſtand acquitted from the Treſpaſſes againſt the Firſt Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and having not ſinned againſt the Grace of the Second Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, they cannot come into the Condemnation of Helliſh Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, as <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Witneſs the Maſſacre in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> Cruel as they ſometimes are to the Bodies of Infants, yet are more merciful to their Souls than the <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> For they ſay, That <hi>Infants ſhall only ſuffer the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Loſs, but not of Torment.</hi> Whilſt the other tells the World, <hi>Infants of a Span long are yelling in the flames of Hell.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. That all dying Infants (or Infants in general) are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Members of the vaſt Body (or Catholick Church) of which Chriſt is the Saviour finally, is evident, <hi>becauſe they are all in a viſible ſtate of Salvation:</hi> And I think no Man will deny the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church to contain the whole number of the ſaved; I have nothing more to do therefore but to prove all Infants are in a viſible ſtate of Salvation, which I ſhall further clear, by anſwering what is objected againſt their Salvation, by Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> my preſent <hi>Adverſary,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Page</hi> 9.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:206466:6"/>
                     <head>SECT. III.</head>
                     <p>
                        <q>I gave you thanks before for ſome things before granted concerning In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and I here promiſe more thanks if you will prove the ſame of all Infants.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſwer.</label> When I ſpeak of the Right which Infants have to Life by Chriſt, I intend it only of that Right derived to them by the firſt Edition of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. wherein they are <hi>equally</hi> concern'd, and ſo have the <hi>ſame</hi> Right. And I hope you will not ſay that any Infant did forfeit this gracious Right by abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Grace of the Covenant. And then Mr. <hi>B.</hi> tells you the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>is not vain, nor repealed by God, nor they caſt out of it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>My Proves are ſuch as theſe: Infants are either all Saved, (dying ſuch) or ſome of them are Damned. But none of them are Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, therefore they are all Saved. <hi>See more of this anon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>It is not the Will of his Heavenly Father, that one of thoſe little ones ſhould periſh;</hi> which is certainly as true of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, as of any Perſons in the World.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Chriſt dying for all Infants, and they do not ſin themſelves out of the benefit of his Death. Shortly thus, God will not Damn any (no not one) of theſe little ones; Men and Devils cannot Damn them; they cannot Damn themſelves. <hi>Ergo,</hi> Chriſt's dying for them will ſave them all. See the concluſion of this Treatiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. IIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B. Pag. 11.</label> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>The overthrow of both theſe Generations in the Deluge, is a ſtrange Medium to prove the Salvation of all Infants,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſwer,</label> I do not ſay, that God's deſtroying the Infants of thoſe that were called his Sons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. as well as the Infants of others, was an Evidence of God's ſaving any of them: But this I do ſay, That it was an Evidence that they were all in one State, or Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cament.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206466:6"/> And how would you (or any Body elſe) prove ſo much as one Infant in all the Old World was ſaved eternally, better than I ſhall prove the Salvation of them all? And ſhall we ſuffer it to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into our Hearts, that they were all Damned? When therefore we reade, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 5. That God <hi>brought the Flood upon the World of the ungodly.</hi> And <hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 7. 'tis ſaid of thoſe who ſuffered the Vengeance of Eternal Fire, That they were <hi>given over to Fornication,</hi> and went <hi>after ſtrange Fleſh;</hi> may we not perceive ſome Light which may guide us to believe, that God did not plead in ſuch Wrath againſt the Infant-ſeed, as he did againſt the Wicked themſelves? And though it is true, God ſuffered the Infants to die with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Parents, yet that is no Argument of God's condemning them to Hell Torments: For did not the ſame God ſuffer his Servant <hi>Sampſon.</hi> to die by the fall of the <hi>Theatre,</hi> among the wicked <hi>Philiſtines?</hi> And we ſee the Righteous often taken away by the ſame common Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which have befallen Nations and Cities. Let us remember how tender the Lord was of the Infants in <hi>Nineveh;</hi> and it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us he was tender to Infants in the <hi>Old World:</hi> And he that made thoſe little ones an Argument to juſtifie his ſparing <hi>Nineveh, (againſt the murmuring of</hi> Jonah) would certainly make that an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for us to believe, That had his Judgments proceeded againſt that City according to the Propheſie of <hi>Jonah,</hi> yet he would have diſtinguiſhed between the Innocent and the Nocent, in reſpect to their future State and Condition; for it was not the Wickedneſs of the Infants <hi>which cried to Heaven,</hi> but of the Adult.</p>
                     <p>When we conſider how hardly Almighty God was drawn to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict thoſe Judgments upon Mens Bodies (though grievous Sinners) in the <hi>Old World,</hi> in <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 18. and frequently where we reade of the Execution of his Judgments, it may juſtly ſeem very ſtrange, that Men ſhould think that God can be ſo eaſily provoked to damn Infants to Hell Torments for him (I ſay) to damn poor Infants in Eternal Fire, who was ſo hardly drawn to Inflict on the <hi>Ninevites</hi> Children ſo much as a Temporal Judgment! Nay, he is unwilling to deſtroy the very Cattel for Man's Sin, <hi>Jonah</hi> 4. which are only capable of Temporal Puniſhment. And can it become us to think that God will ſend Millions, or any poor dying Babes to Hell? And pray what have they done thus highly to ſtir up his Wrath againſt them? Shew the Cauſe if you can.</p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:206466:7"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>To the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. The Free-gift abounded towards all Men to Juſtification of Life. You anſwer, <hi>This all muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to all in Chriſt.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>But by your favour, There is none ſo out of Chriſt as they come into the World, but God hath provided Mercy for them in Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1. 29. ſo that here is no reſtraint of the Juſtification here ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, till Men abuſe the Mercy of God by ſinning againſt their own Souls. Nor can your reſtriction [which I ſuppoſe would limit this Free-gift to the Elect only] hold agreement with the ſcope of the place; for ſeeing Mankind, or all Men, are Perſonated as well in the ſecond, as in the Firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> 
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>The Law entered, that Sin might abound; but where Sin abounded, Grace did much more abound. That,</hi> as <hi>Sin hath reigned unto Death,</hi> even ſo <hi>might Grace reign through Righteouſneſs unto Eternal Life by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
                        </note> You can no more exclude any from the Juſtification of Life [as having abounded towards them by Chriſt] than you can exclude them from the Condemnation [which abounded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Men] by the Firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> For tell me, How many came under Condemnation by the Sin of <hi>Adam?</hi> Is there any (or any Infant) that can plead Impunity? Why <hi>even ſo,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>the Free-gift came upon all Men to Juſtification of Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And may we not now ſafely conclude, that had Mankind never been guilty of any other Sin, but that (I ſay, upon a ſuppoſition, that <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity, had from the time of the Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. lived holily, and done no Iniquity) would you not conclude with me, that none ſhould have periſhed in Helliſh Torments? And if you grant this, then we muſt either find ſome Man, SO con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd <hi>in the Covenant of Grace,</hi> AS, that if he ſinned againſt it, his <hi>Poſterity</hi> is <hi>condemned with him Eternally;</hi> as all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity were expoſed to Condemnation for his Sin: Or elſe we muſt hold, that no Infant ſhall die eternally for <hi>Adam</hi>'s, nor for any other Perſons iniquity. If you name any Man <hi>thus</hi> concern'd in the Covenant of Grace, you can name none ſo apt for the purpoſe as <hi>Adam,</hi> ſeeing we were all in him when that Covenant was made with him, and there is no doubt but that he ſinned after the Covenant was made, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. Yet where do we find any Sin which he afterward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, imputed to any part of his Poſterity? And ſeeing we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove an Univerſal Reſurrection from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21, 22. unleſs Mankind be equally concern'd in the Death of Chriſt. We muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206466:7"/> neceſſarily believe whole Mankind to be intereſſed in him, and as they are intereſſed in Chriſt they are ſaved of the Lord; and in him they are as clearly intereſſed in God's Mercy, as they were Objects of his Wrath by the firſt Man: So being juſtified from the guilt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of poor Infants, that may juſtly caſt them into Hell Fire? ſure 'tis but meet Men ſhould be able plainly to Convict them, before they thus Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them. Yea, you that hold the Eternal Damnation of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, ought you not to bring ſubſtantial Proof for ſo dreadful a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? And when you have done your worſt that way, you have only deſtroyed your own certainty of Comfort concerning your dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants; for I am perſuaded you are not ſo unwiſe to think (whatever you make others believe) that your Infants are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaved becauſe of your pretended Church-Memberſhip and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; ſeeing 'tis too evident that many attain to that Eſtate, and yet are unlikely to be ſaved.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. V.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B. pag. 13.</label>—<q>
                           <hi>To aſſert the Salvation of all that die in Infancy, ſeems to imply that God's deſtroying the Old World and</hi> Sodom, <hi>&amp;c. were eminent Acts of God's Mercy rather than of Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>help me over this Difficulty.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> Although it is not unjuſt for God to take Infants out of the World, yet his Juſtice <hi>in deſtroying the Old World and Sodom,</hi> lay not againſt the Infants (as I proved in the Section next before) but in Juſtice he puniſhed thoſe wicked Parents in putting a period to their Poſterity. Did not God in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> deſtroy all Beaſts and Fowls (almoſt)? yet who ſo weak to think he was offended with them, was the Lord angry with the Beaſts of the Field?</p>
                     <p>God was juſt in taking away <hi>David</hi>'s Child, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 12. 14, yet who ſo raſh to ſay, That God did this in point of Juſtice againſt the Child? Or that God was angry with the Child? much leſs that the Child was damned. <hi>David</hi> was far from any ſuch opinion; for though that Child was conceived and born in Sin and Iniquity, as much as well could be, and doubtleſs had the imputation of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Sin, as much as any, yet <hi>David</hi> nothing feared that Child's
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206466:8"/> damnation, but rather intimates his confidence of its Salvation, when he ſaid, <hi>I ſhall go to it.</hi> For had it gone to Hell Torments, he would not have comforted himſelf with thoughts of going to it.</p>
                     <p>I cannot make your ſpeech to agree with the Juſtice of God, where you ſay, <hi>That Infants periſh not purely for another's Sin, but for their own contracted.</hi> For though I can hear Men talk big words againſt Infants, as if they were little better than Devils, yet I never ſaw any proof that any Infant had any Sin of its own, for which you would here make them periſh, or at leaſt ſome of them; The Scripture ſaith, <hi>Sin is the tranſgreſſion of a Law,</hi> and tells us alſo, that where no Law is there is NO TRANSGRESSION. You muſt therefore either ſhew ſome Law to be given to Infants, or elſe you cannot make them guilty, of any Sin of their own. And though I have not ſeen Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book to which you refer me, yet I do not deny Original Sin, for I know it is come upon all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and Death paſſeth upon them, for that all have ſinned in him. Howbeit, I do believe that all Infants are as clearly juſtified from the condemning power of Sin, in reſpect of Damnation, as any Saint whatſoever, which I think I have alſo proved from <hi>John</hi> 1. 29. and other places. And ſeeing you now grant <hi>that none ſhall periſh purely for another's Sin,</hi> it remains for you to ſhew what Sin (excepting <hi>Adam</hi>'s) is come upon any Infant, to render him ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Damnation. You talk of <hi>their Contracting Sin</hi> of their own, but I am to learn how this can be truly ſaid of them, that neither Act, nor conſent to Sin at all; and ſurely ſuch Scriptureleſs Notions are fitter to be exploded than embraced.</p>
                     <p>And though you ſeem to have ſome Charity <hi>for thoſe, and their Seed, that only come up to the Covenant of Grace made with</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Noah <hi>(though they never heard the Goſpel) whilſt you ſay, you do not rank them with Infidels.</hi> Yet this is but a ſlender kindneſs, you do not ſay they ſhall be ſaved. And you are poſitive in this, <hi>That In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are not ſaved by the Covenant of Grace, if they neither be Believers, nor the Seed of ſuch,</hi> Page 17.</p>
                     <p>How this Doctrine will ſtand with the juſtice of a Gracious God, I cannot conceive; when I conſider that God hath neither given to Infants a capacity to believe, nor any liberty to chuſe whether they will be the Seed of Believers, or Unbelievers. Will you yet ſay, the moſt High will be more harſh in the Acts of Juſtice, than the Rules
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206466:8"/> will bear which he hath given to Men, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 25, 26?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is not the part of a wiſe Legiſlator</hi> (ſaith a learned Man of the Church of <hi>England) to recede from his own Laws,</hi> much leſs to deſtroy them by acting contrary to them. It muſt be a fault then, in you thus to repreſent the God of Juſtice; Is the Covenant of Grace ſet upon ſuch a tickle point, as that the greateſt part of Infants cannot poſſibly have any benefit by it? So you teach who affirm they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaved <hi>by the Covenant of Grace, unleſs they be Believers, or the Seed of ſuch.</hi> Why call you a Covenant made on ſuch terms, a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace to Infants? Sure impoſſible Terms in a Covenant are not very gracious. You would condemn this in Men, you would not accept ſuch terms of Man, eſpecially when the non-obſervance of ſuch Terms took away the benefit of the Covenant; yet thus you make many believe, that God deals with the greateſt part of Infants. But I ſhall return to your former Inſtances of God's Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt Infants (as you would have it) to wit, the deſtruction <hi>of the Old World and Sodom.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                     <p>The taking away by Death the Infants in the Old World and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> is neither an inſtance of Juſtice nor Mercy in the main to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, any more than the taking away thouſands of Infants daily by death throughout the World. For when ever they die, they are taken away from the evil to come, and ſo it is always a Mercy; and ſo it was a Mercy to the Infants of the Old World, and the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents in <hi>Sodom.</hi> But when ever they are taken away, we know it is for Sin, even that of <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſometimes their death is haſtened for the Sin of the Parents (as in the caſe of <hi>David</hi>'s Child before mentioned, as well as the Old World, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and thus their being taken away is always a Judgment. And the Judgment lieth much in this, that Mens Poſterity is hereby either quite cut off, or greatly weakened; and thus the <hi>Old World</hi> and <hi>Sodom</hi> were puniſhed, in that they were deprived of all Succeſſion.</p>
                     <p>And though it be true (as you urge) <hi>That if theſe Infants in the Old World and</hi> Sodom <hi>had lived to Age, many of them might have been Damned for wickedneſs.</hi> Yet to ballance that, it is as true, that a far greater Multitude in a few Generations, both of Infants and others,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206466:9"/> which might have proceeded from them, might have been ſaved; ſo that though we have no ground to doubt of the Salvation of the dying Infants in the Old World, and <hi>Sodom,</hi> yet we may ſee a moſt juſt Judgment of the Lord executed in both.</p>
                     <p>Of the ſame conſideration is your Inſtance of <hi>Countries and Cities Deſtroyed and Depopulated by Tyrannical Princes,</hi> Pag. 14. For what it the <hi>French King</hi> (as you write) ſhould deſtroy all the Infants of the <hi>Pagans,</hi> with the Adult, it neither follows that here is not a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from God in all this, neither yet that God hath no Mercy for thoſe Infants. But pray conſider, whilſt we all condemn ſuch a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> as ſhould ſo barbarouſly Murther ſo many Innocents, we may by no means ſay, or think, that a Gracious God, will now, when the Tyrant hath murthered them, take and caſt them into Hell-fire; for he is a God that delights in Mercy. But here you cry out, <hi>Had the World your Light and Knowledg, they ought not to be ſorry for the ſpoiling of their Countries, but rejoyce that all their little Ones are ſaved.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But this is a non-ſequiter: <hi>For no Man may do Evil that Good may come:</hi> and let us not murmur againſt God, who when Men have done their worſt, he knows how to prevent that which might be far worſe than the worſt they can do to Infants: And though I may be ſatisfied that my dead Child, or Friend, is gone to Heaven, yet I may lawfully be ſorry for his Death.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>
                           <hi>J. B. Pag.</hi> 15.</label> 
                        <q>And what ſhall we make of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 3. &amp; <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>And were by Nature Children of Wrath, even as others. That at that time you were without Chriſt,—without Hope.</hi> If there be no ground to doubt the Salvation of their Infants, is there not ſome hope?</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> I grant that all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, with himſelf, were Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath; and take that Wrath in as large a ſence as you pleaſe, it hurts not my Cauſe at all, ſeeing it is evident that Chriſt aboliſhed that Wrath and Death, and brought Life and Immortality to light by the Goſpel, which he preached to whole <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 3. 15. and then took whole <hi>Adam</hi> into his Grace and Favour; ſo that till they,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206466:9"/> or any of them become the Serpents ſeed, they ſtand in a ſtate of Favour and Grace, which ſhall deliver them from Wrath and Death. And it is moſt certain no Infant is the Serpent's ſeed, it being out of his power to beget them to be his Off-ſpring, ſeeing they are out of the reach of his Temptations during Infancy.</p>
                     <p>Howbeit, this place <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. is beſt interpreted, of the Adult, or grown Perſons: For thoſe of whom it is ſaid, <hi>They were without Hope,</hi> &amp;c. it is ſaid, they were <hi>dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the courſe of this World, according to the Prince of the power of the Air, which now worketh in the hearts of the Children of Diſobedience;</hi> ſuch as <hi>had their Converſation in the luſts of their Fleſh, fulfilling the deſires of the Fleſh and of the Mind, and</hi> (SO) <hi>were by Nature the Children of Wrath.</hi> But what is all this to the innocent Babes of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they were not thus the Children of Wrath, No, nor out of the Covenant of Grace as made with <hi>Adam,</hi> having never abuſed the Grace of that Covenant, ſo that here was Hope (or ground of Hope) concerning the dying Infants of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whether their Parents underſtood it or not, but no hope concerning themſelves, conſidered in their wicked Courſes.</p>
                     <p>Neither could the Hope of theſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> when they believed concerning their Infants, ſtand upon the ſame grounds, on which their own Hopes was founded; ſeeing, theſe were <hi>ſaved through Faith,</hi> and <hi>built up an Habitation of God through the Spirit.</hi> Only this is very true, They now underſtood the riches of God's Grace to Mankind, and that God had pity for them <hi>when they were dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins,</hi> and therefore they could not rationally doubt of his good will towards their dying Infants; for ſtill his unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to deſtroy the actual Sinner, is argument enough that he will never deſtroy the innocent Child eternally.</p>
                     <p>What hope there is of all Infants entering into Heaven (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may be hid from the Pagans) is evident enough from our Saviours Speech, <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as little Children, ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Now ſuppoſe I take the Infant of a <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi> for my pattern, and labour that my Converſion may anſwer to ſuch a preſident in point of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, Humility and Simplicity, will not this as well accord with the intent of our Saviour's Words, as if I took the Child of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian for my pattern? <hi>Certes</hi> it would; and indeed our Saviour here ſpeaks as much for our comfort concerning all little Childrens capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:206466:10"/> to enter into Heaven, as for any one of them. As alſo when the Apoſtle exhorts us as touching Malice, to be as Children, does he not hereby juſtifie the whole in that ſtate of Childhood to be devoid of that evil? And why even of our ſelves do we not judge what is right? Could any Man from the beginning to this Day, bring the leaſt charge againſt an Infant, much leſs againſt one Infant more than another? unleſs God by Miracle ſhews ſome ſpecial Power up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, no difference can be ſeen in them in point of Innocency.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>But have you not forgotten that you told us, you do not doubt but the Promiſes made to the Seed of the Righteous, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of ſhewing Mercy to the Children of them that love God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>remain unrevoked?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> I have not forgotten that, but do ſtill believe that there are many more Bleſſings pertaining to the Seed of the Righteous (according to the Texts by you alledged) than to others. And that they may be the better conſidered, I will ſet that down in Words, which you writ in Figures. Pſal. 102. 28. <hi>The Children of thy Servants ſhall continue, and their Seed ſhall be eſtabliſhed before thee.</hi> This had doubtleſs been the Portion of the Sons of God in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> had they not ſinned with the reſt of Mankind. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 17. <hi>But the Mercy of the Lord is from everlaſting to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them that fear him, and his Righteouſneſs to Childrens Children, to them that keep his Covenant, and remember his Commandments to do them.</hi> Prov 20. 7. <hi>The Juſt walketh in his Integrity, his Children are bleſſed after him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now what do theſe places prove? Surely nothing leſs, than that no Infants but the Infants of Believers ſhall be ſaved, and if not, how do theſe places ſuit your caſe? They prove indeed that God will bleſs the Poſterity of his faithful Servants, if they keep his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and remember to do his Commandments; and I think <hi>David</hi> well expounds this place in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 25. <hi>I have been Young, and now am Old; yet did I never ſee the Righteous forſaken, nor their Seed begging their Bread.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:206466:10"/>
                     <p> And yet I grant (though you prove it not) that there are many other advantages (even in Infancy) attends the Seed of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, they being a Seed of many Prayers, and devoted to God from the Womb, as far as their pious Parents has authority to do it (which I have more fully ſet down in my Book of <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity, L.</hi> 2. <hi>P.</hi> 5, 6.) whiles God knows others are deſtitute of theſe Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, being <hi>Croſſed</hi> and <hi>Exorcis'd,</hi> &amp;c. among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Molech</hi> among the <hi>Jews;</hi> and the like among the Heathens. And yet for all this I can ſee no ground to think that the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God will puniſh with Hell Torments thoſe dying Infants, for the wrong which their Parents have done them. It being to me inconceivable, how it can ſtand with his glorious Attributes, either of Mercy or Juſtice, both which muſt have effect upon theſe Infants. His Juſtice hath effect upon them; that is evident, in their Death, Sickneſs, and Diſeaſes (and the like befalls our Infants); now ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Mercy muſt have effect upon them in the next World, or not at all, and if not in that World, how then ſhall that ſaying hold true, <hi>His tender Mercies are over all his Works?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. IX.</head>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>You would not have the bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>(as it concerns Eternal Life) to reach to the Infants of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, becauſe</hi> Gal. 3. 14. <hi>it's ſaid to come upon the</hi> Gentiles <hi>by Faith.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>Anſw.</label> I told you that the <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> in reſpect of Eternal Life, was not peculiar to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, but was made as well to <hi>Adam</hi> and his Seed, and ſo common to Mankind, and may well be called the Common Salvation, being derived from Chriſt, promiſed <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. (before <hi>Abraham</hi> was) who is therefore the Saviour of all Men. Indeed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo all Believers, have ſome things in ſpecial, and which are peculiar to them, as a People engaged in the duties of Religion, <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>See and conſider</hi> Rom. 3. 1, 2.</note> whilſt the Unbeliever is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſentence of Wrath, becauſe <hi>he neglects ſo great Salvation,</hi> Heb. 2. 2, 3, 4. But all this injures not dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants who neglect not this Salvation, and ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit not their right to that common Salvation obtained by Chriſt for Mankind.</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:206466:11"/>
                     <p> In <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 14. the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the <hi>Promiſe of the Spirit,</hi> which as it concerns the Church under the eſtabliſhment of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Covenant, concerns not Infants, it being underſtood of a greater meaſure of Wiſdom, and Power, to walk in the Paths of Righteouſneſs, than was ordinary under the former Teſtament, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 2, 3, 5, 7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 25.</p>
                     <p>Nor can you (with any ſhew of Reaſon) ſay that I make the Salvation of Infants run in a Fleſhly Line, when I derive it only from the Free-grace of God manifeſted in the <hi>Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the World, to take away the Sin of the World.</hi> Nor do I conſider <hi>Adam</hi> as in a ſtate of Nature, but as under a Covenant of Grace, from whom the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> muſt in time proceed as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fleſh, and therefore his Deſcent is reckoned from him, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 23. <hi>to the end.</hi> In this ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Repairer of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, do I place the Salvation of all Men; and of the Infant Race, I ſay, ſeeing they never ſinned againſt the ſecond Covenant, nor can any other ſin them out of the Mercy of God; their title to that Grace being not tide to Man's Will, it follows that they ſhall not be hurt of the ſecond Death: Shew the contrary if you can.</p>
                     <p>To what you ſay about <hi>God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s putting the Salvation of Infants out of his own Hand.</hi> I ſay, That though he put the Salvation of no Creature out of his own Hand, according to my opinion, yet when he ſtretcheth forth his Hand to Gain-ſayers, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. and gives them the Word of Life, and they put it from them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 46. then Men may truly be ſaid to have a Prize in their Hand, and to put it from them, even the Salvation of their Souls. And then I pray you conſider, that if their putting Salvation from them be equally, or really a putting it from their Infants (as that muſt be your opinion, or elſe we differ not) then I ſay, according to your opinion, God ſuffers Men to damn poor Infants whom he would ſave, ſeeing (according to your Doctrine) had their Parents belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, their Infants had been in the Covenant of Grace, but now for their Fathers Sin (for what you ſay of their own Sin contracted is but a Fable) they are left by you in the Kingdom of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and that among the Devil and his Angels for ever. <hi>And here it is that I oppoſe you, as greatly erring from the Truth, and this Error was that which firſt brought in your Pedo-baptiſm; as may be ſeen in the Decree made by the</hi> African <hi>Council,</hi> 
                        <note n="†" place="margin">The words of the Council are theſe, <hi>All that affirm young Children receive Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, albeit they be not by Baptiſm renewed, they are accurſed,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>where</hi> Auguſtine <hi>was preſent</hi>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:206466:11"/> 
                        <hi>and Preſident.</hi> Wherefore, remove but this Error, and the other will preſently vaniſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="section">
                     <head>SECT. X.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>The Sum of this Controverſy.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>I will finiſh this Diſcourſe by ſetting down certain Propoſitions, which contain the whole Controverſy; and which I hope will carry ſo much Light and Evidence in them, as may tend much to the ſatisfaction of the Reader. The thing to be cleared is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That no dying Infants are Damned, or all dying Infants are Saved.</hi> Which will thus be made good.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="subsection">
                        <head>1. <hi>Becauſe they cannot damn themſelves.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>And it is moſt certain, God will not Damn any to Hell Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who do not firſt Damn themſelves in ſinful Courſes. This is evident by his unwillingneſs to deſtroy thoſe that had ſo deſtroyed themſelves, Hoſ. 13. 9. <hi>O Iſrael, thou haſt deſtroyed thy ſelf, but in me is thy help.</hi> If then our God be thus unwilling to deſtroy thoſe that have deſtroyed themſelves, as that he will help and ſave them; how ſhould it enter into the Heart of a Chriſtian to imagine, that the ſame God will Damn poor Infants, who never deſtroyed themſelves, neither can they do it?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="subsection">
                        <head>2. <hi>No Man can damn Infants.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>This is evident; becauſe if any Man have power to damn Infants, every Man hath the ſame, for it cannot be proved the peculiar pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (whether good or bad) of any Man. And if any will ſay, that every Man hath power to damn his Children, he ſpeaks preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly; there is nothing in the Word of God to countenance ſuch a Doctrine: for the contrary is plain, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 30. <hi>Every one ſhall die for his own iniquity.</hi> This is meant (or is moſt true) of Eternal Death, becauſe we all die the firſt Death for the Sin of another,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206466:12"/> to wit, <hi>Adam;</hi> and though this ſaying be true of the Adult, yet it is the more to our purpoſe, becauſe if God be ſo gracious to actual Sinners as not to damn them for the Sin of another, there is all the ground imaginable to believe that he will be as gracious to Infants.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="subsection">
                        <head>3. <hi>The Devil cannot damn Infants.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>This is evident, becauſe Infants are out of the reach of Santan's Temptations, ſeeing they know not to chuſe the Good, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it; they know neither Good nor Evil, they know not their right Hand from their left, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 16. <hi>Jonah</hi> 4. 11. Whom Satan cannot Tempt, them he cannot Damn.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="subsection">
                        <head>4. <hi>God will not damn Infants.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>God will not ſuffer Men to puniſh any Perſon for that which they cannot help. Deut. 22. 25, 26. <hi>If a Man find a betrothed Damſel in the Field, and force her, and lie with her, then the Man only that lay with her ſhall die; but unto the Damſel ſhalt thou do nothing, there is in the Damſel no Sin worthy of Death. For as when a Man riſeth up againſt his Neighbour and ſlayeth him, even ſo is this matter.</hi> The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which God ſheweth in this caſe, may ſuffice to convince us, that in the Judgment of the Almighty there is no Sin in Infants worthy of Damnation, ſeeing what Sin ſoever is upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> was impoſſible for them to avoid it: Wherefore he will not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> poor dying Infants.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="subsection">
                        <head>5. <hi>Chriſt will not damn poor Infants.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>When Chriſt denounceth the Damnation of Hell, he dir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſpeech to Hypocrites, and incorrigible Sinners. Mat. 23. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>: <hi>Generation of Vipers, how can ye eſcape the Damnation of Hell?</hi> But he hath better things in ſtore for Infants, for he ſaith, <hi>of ſuch are the Kingdom of God;</hi> which being ſpoken of Infants, or little Children indefinitly, ſhews his Gracious Judgment of them all. And he that came <hi>not to Condemn the World,</hi> but <hi>to Save the World,</hi> how ſhall this be true, if he came to Condemn any Infants? Seeing there are no Perſons in the World, who do leſs deſerve Damnation than In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; No, not his own Diſciples, who are therefore ſent to little
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206466:12"/> Children, to know how to enter the Kingdom of Heaven. Mark 10. 15 <hi>Verily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> you, whoſoever ſhall not receive the Kingdom of God as a litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> ſhall not enter therein.</hi> What Believer can think himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Heaven than an Infant? Hath he not ſome Actual Sin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> no Infant? Hath Chriſt freed the Believer from Original Sin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>e he hath done for all Infants. Rom. 5. <hi>As in</hi> Adam <hi>all d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> John 1. 29 <hi>Behold the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> God, which taketh away the Sin of the World.</hi> There i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Sin can ſo properly be called the Sin of the World, as Origin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>, becauſe perhaps a third part of the World dies, having no other Sin at all. This is the caſe of Infants, this Sin being taken a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>hriſt, how ſhall Chriſt their merciful Judg pronounce them<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Hell?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="subsection">
                        <head>6. <hi>Chriſt died <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> Infants, therefore they ſhall not be damned.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Chriſt died <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Infants, <hi>Becauſe he gave himſelf a Ranſom for all,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 6. <hi>He taſted Death for every Man,</hi> Heb. 2. 9. <hi>He bought them that deny him,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. Therefore certainly he was as graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Infants, as to thoſe who deny him. Seeing then it cannot be denied but he bought them, he either bought them to ſave them, or to caſt them to Hell. Not the latter, no by no means: The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary end of Chriſt's dying is Life and Salvation. Infants never forfeit this Grace, but are juſt Perſons that need no Repentance, if there be any ſuch in the World.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="subsection">
                        <head>7. <hi>All dying Infants are written in the Book of Life from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World, therefore no dying Infants are Damned.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>The Omniſcient God knew as well the Date of all Mens Lives, as that they ſhould be born or live at all, and therefore did he know who would die in Infancy, as well as who would live to years of Knowledg. Admitting then their opinion to be true, <hi>That hold a certain number ordain'd to Life from the Foundation of the World,</hi> yet we doubt not but to make good this Propoſition, and that by the Text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. 12. <hi>as expounded by themſelves.</hi> For by the Books, out of which the Damned are judged, is underſtood the Actions of Men, even the moſt ſecret, which ſhall then be laid open. Now theſe Books cannot concern Infants, they having done neither good
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206466:13"/> nor evil. Here is therefore another Book opened, which (ſay they) repreſents the everlaſting Election to Life and Glory in Chriſt. In this Book muſt all dying Infants either be found writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or elſe be Judged without Book. The Book of Conſcience will not accuſe them, therefore the Lamb's Book of Life muſt needs acquit them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="subsection">
                        <head>8. <hi>All dying Infants are in the Covenant of Grace; therefore no dying Infant ſhall be Damned.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>When we ſay Infants are in the Covenant of Grace, we mean it, as God hath vouchſafed to intereſs them in his Mercy by Chriſt. That as Condemnation came upon them by <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin, ſo Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Life might abound towards them by the Obedience of Chriſt. Now either Infants are thus in Covenant with God, or they are not concern'd in any Covenant at all. For the Covenant of pure Nature (as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> terms it) made with <hi>Adam,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not Infants, but as the breach of it is imputed to the Lump of Mankind. And the Law of Works concerns not Infants. For to them it cannot be ſaid, <hi>The Man that doth theſe things, ſhall live in them.</hi> And to ſay Infants are in no Covenant with God, is to rank them with Devils, and the vileſt of Men. But ſeeing Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> grants the Covenant made with <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 9. to be the Covenant of Grace, and the Scripture tells us, <hi>That it is an everlaſting Covenant, and made with</hi> Noah <hi>and his Sons, and with their Seed after them,</hi> and conſequently with all Infants; for it is not Vain, or Repealed, till Men abuſe the Mercy of it; to this Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> conſents. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſhould it be otherwiſe, God ſhould deal worſe with poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, than with the Beaſts of the Field; for he was pleaſed to make a Covenant with them (even every living Creature of them) which alſo was very gracious according to their ſtate and condition: and ſhall we think that he whoſe tender Mercies are over all his Works, will exclude the Infants of the greateſt part of Mankind from his Gracious Covenant? No: He hath ſaid, <hi>He will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Covenant which he hath made with all Fleſh,</hi> Gen. 9.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="subsection">
                        <head>9. <hi>No Man can prove that any Infant ever was, or ever ſhall be damned in Hell Torments; therefore no dying Infant ſhall be damned.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>There is nothing to be held as an Opinion, or Point of Faith, but upon clear Proof, or Rational Demonſtration. Now though it has
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:206466:13"/> been often delivered from the Pulpits, that many Infants are yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Hell (yea, Infants of a Span long) for ſuch and ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of their Parents, yet this is only ſaid, but no proof to make it good. I find Dr. <hi>Fulk</hi> ſaying, <hi>That</hi> Calvin <hi>holdeth</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Dr.</hi> Fulk.</note> 
                           <hi>all Infants under the ſentence of eternal Damnation;</hi> only he admits, that <hi>ſuch Infants as are Elect, and Born again by the Spirit of God, may be ſaved.</hi> But I find no proof that any Infants are Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated to eternal Damnation; neither does the holy Scripture ſay any ſuch thing. And whilſt <hi>Diodate</hi> expounds <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 12. modeſtly and ſoundly, he goes back to his harſh opinion of God's caſting <hi>Eſau</hi> (when or before he was born) out of his Love as a Father, (in what he ſays upon the 13th <hi>ver.)</hi> as if God's Love were taken away from poor Infants. But this is no proof that God hath Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any dying Infant: for if we admit their Gloſs, yet God that knew what <hi>Eſau</hi> would be in time, did here foreſhew what in time ſhould be effected. <hi>Eſau</hi> lived to be a Man, and a very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>l Man, God knew all this before; <hi>Eſau</hi> is not to be ranked wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>ying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, therefore the Inſtance of <hi>Eſau</hi> is nothing to the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>oſe; and this Inſtance failing (as it evidently doth) I am ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>here is not the leaſt ſhew of proof in the Scripture, for the Damnation of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants; and therefore no Man ought to believe ſuch a ſtrange and windy Doctrine, nor trouble the World (nor the Church) about it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="subsection">
                        <head>10. <hi>To hold Infants to be Damned, is contrary to all good Reaſon.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> prayed, <hi>To be delivered from unreaſonable Men, for that all Men had not Faith.</hi> He ſeems to make Reaſon a Friend, and no Enemy to Faith. Now when we hear that wicked Men ſhall <hi>be damned, becauſe they received not the Love of the Truth that they might be ſaved;</hi> here Reaſon preſently conſents to the Judgment of God. And when we hear that Men will not be perſuaded by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, or one that ſhould riſe from the Dead; how juſtly are they puniſhed by that God whoſe Grace they have ſo groſsly contemned? Yea, theſe and many like Inſtances, are according to the common Rules of Juſtice. But now to place poor innocent Babes among theſe damned ones, that they ſhould be tormented with the Devil and his Angels, who only was born to cry and die, and ſometimes to die before they ſhould cry, is ſo cruel a Conceit, ſo inconſiſtent with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice (as far as the Reaſon of Man can conceive what is equal) that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206466:14"/> nothing can be more Cruel. It looks as if God took pleaſure to ſend poor Creatures to Hell. For theſe poor Infants (many of them according to this Scriptureleſs Doctrine) were but created on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be Damned, and nothing elſe; ſome never ſeeing ſo much as the Light of this World, and yet muſt be puniſhed with the Devil to Eternity. O ſhameful Doctrine! unfit for the Tongue of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, to tell the World, Infants (yea, of a Span long) are yelling in Hell! Will you charge the God <hi>of Love,</hi> yea, that God who <hi>is Love,</hi> with theſe Cruelties? Are theſe his doings? Why have you painted him in your Sermons with ſuch bloody Colours? Is it to force on your <hi>Pedo-rantiſm?</hi> O wretched Cauſe, that cannot ſtand unleſs the Mercy of God to the greateſt part of Infants be impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! We ſay not that Reaſon is the chief judge in this Queſtion, yet when we meet with Scriptureleſs Doctrines, 'tis not unlawful to refute them by Reaſon. And here I again declare, that this Error of holding Infants damned without Baptiſm, was the ground of that innovation of Pedo-baptiſm. For thus ſaith the 5 <hi>Con. de Carth. We will that whoever denies that little Children by Baptiſm are freed from Perdition, and eternally ſaved, that they be accurſed.</hi> Wherefore take away this falſe ground, by ſhewing the Salvation of all dying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, and then INFANT-BAPTISM vaniſheth.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:206466:14"/>
                  <p> THE QUERIST EXAMINED.</p>
                  <p>The Second Part.</p>
                  <p>WHEREIN More than Sixty <hi>Queries,</hi> taken out of the Works of Mr. <hi>R. Baxter,</hi> by <hi>J. B.</hi> (the Author of Fifty former <hi>Queries)</hi> are Refuted, BY A proportionable Number of <hi>Antiqueries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>SHEWING The Inſufficiency of the Plea for Infant-Baptiſm urged by Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> from their viſible Church-Memberſhip.</p>
                  <p>WHICH Being granted (ſo far, and in ſuch a ſenſe) as Truth or Reaſon will Warrant, is againſt, and no way for the Baptizing of Infants.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>THOMAS GRANTHAM.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed in the Year, 1679.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:206466:15"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="division">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:206466:15"/>
                  <head>DIVISION I.</head>
                  <argument>
                     <p>About the ſilence of the Scripture concerning Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
                  </argument>
                  <p>IT is certain, That to multiply Queſtions is the ready way to darken Counſel, and to intangle the underſtanding of the weak or unwary Reader. Yet thus hath Mr. <hi>J. B.</hi> been pleaſed to incumber the Doctrine of Baptiſm with more than an hundred <hi>Queries;</hi> which being ſet down in their exact Number, would be more than five hundred <hi>Queries.</hi> By which frivolous way of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it were eaſie to involve the Chriſtian Profeſſion in endleſs Controverſies.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, as I have formerly redargued the firſt Book of his <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> ſo (leſt he ſhould ſuppoſe theſe to be unanſwerable) I think it may do ſome ſervice to the Truth, to ſhew briefly the vanity of his ſecond Book alſo.</p>
                  <p>It would make my work too bulkie to ſet down his <hi>Queries</hi> at large, yet I ſhall endeavour partly by what I ſhall preſent <hi>of his Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and partly by the purport of my <hi>Anti-queries,</hi> to give a true underſtanding of the import of all his Demands. And firſt we ſhall take notice of his Preparatory Queſtions, which he grounds upon <hi>the ſilence of the Scriptures in the caſe of Infant-Baptiſm.</hi> The firſt is this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>1. <hi>Is not the Scripture more ſparing in ſuch caſes as theſe,</hi> 1. <hi>In ſpeaking of thoſe, to whom it ſpeaks not, as concerning the Heathen, and concerning Infants?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label> 1. When Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (and you from him) have born the World in hand, that you would offer plain Scripture proof for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm; Is it not a ſtrange way to make this good, by telling us the Scripture is more ſilent in theſe Caſes than in others? Or is not one plain proof in any Caſe enough
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:206466:16"/> to forbid any to ſay, the Scripture is more ſilent in that than other Caſes, ſeeing <hi>more ſilent,</hi> muſt import <hi>not ſpeaking at all,</hi> or elſe <hi>very darkly.</hi> And indeed, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> does elſewhere grant, <hi>That many Papiſts and Prelatiſts (who are all for Infant Baptiſm) have maintained that it is not determined in Scripture.</hi> And how then ſhall he (being inferiour to ſo many) bring any <hi>plain Scripture</hi> for it? 2. Is not the Scripture plain enough, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. that the Covenant of God's Grace and Mercy to Sinners, concerns all Mankind (as they are fallen in <hi>Adam?)</hi> And how then can it be ſilent concerning Infants, in any thing needful to their Salvation, ſeeing Chriſt now by <hi>the Grace of God hath taſted Death for every Man?</hi> Heb. 2. 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>2. <hi>In leſſer points of Faith?</hi> 3. <hi>In points not then queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> 4. <hi>Does not the New Teſtament ſpeak more ſparingly of that which is more fully diſcovered in the Old? And is not this the very caſe here?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>1. Who that is truly wiſe would query this? Is any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm to be reckoned among the leſſer points of Faith? Or, is it not of very great moment (rather) for us rightly to underſtand who ought to be incorporated into the Church of Chriſt, which is his Body? If there was no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in the Scripture-Times about your Infant Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm, was it not becauſe there was none then that held with your Opinion in that Caſe? And whether it be not Anti-evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal to make the Age of any Perſon the rule of his admiſſion to the Chriſtian-Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm, whiles in the Law the Eighth Day was a time prefixed? But is not the time of the New Birth (at what Age ſoever) the time of Incorporating Perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Chriſtian Church? Seeing it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>If any Man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 16, 17. And whether Pedo-Baptiſts muſt not grant this, ſeeing they are forced to ſay of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants which they ſprinkle, <hi>This Child is Regenerate, and Born again</hi> though they can never prove this?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>2. <hi>Will the difficulty of a Point, that is not ſo clear as we would have it, prove that it is not a truth? The Apoſtle</hi> Peter <hi>tells us, many things in</hi> Paul<hi>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Epiſtles are hard to be underſtood, are they not Truths for all this?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Whether it be not idle in you to compare Church-Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Baptiſm, with the hard things in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, ſeeing what is needful to meer <hi>Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm</hi> are eaſie
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:206466:16"/> things, even that which every Babe in Chriſt ſhould know, and which three thouſand learned in one Day, by one <hi>Sermon.</hi> Acts 2. 40, 41. <hi>Then they which gladly received his Word, were Baptized, and the</hi> SAME DAY <hi>was added unto them about three thouſand Souls.</hi> And whether the whole carriage of this place do not ſhew your Vanity, in putting your Church-Memberſhip before Baptiſm, ſith here (as well as elſe-where) this Church-Memberſhip evidently follows Baptiſm?</p>
                  <p>And whether you do not here alſo plainly enough tell us, that your caſe is very difficult, and hard to be underſtood? and indeed you may rightly place it among things unintelligible. For as one of your Way going to a Diſpute, ('tis ſaid) to hear Infant baptiſm proved by Scripture, told his Companion, <hi>He was going to hear a Miracle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>3. <hi>If never ſo clear Evidence be produced, will not Truth ſtill be dark to them that are uncapable of diſcerning it? And is not this the caſe of many Godly, that are but Children in knowledg?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Whether this be not an excellent way to query Men out of their Wits? And if that which hath <hi>never ſo clear Evidence,</hi> may ſtill be dark to the Godly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How can you blame Men for not ſeeing that for which you can bring <hi>no clear Evidence?</hi> But for all this, whether every weak (if a Godly) Man, may not as eaſily underſtand the Mind of God about Church-Memberſhip and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as to know that Jeſus is his Saviour (unleſs your 100, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 500 Queries have blinded his Eyes)? And what one Point, hath been peſtered with ſuch a cloud of Queſtions, as you have invented about this? And whether you and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent as many more, and ſo make good the Proverb, <hi>Plura poteſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogare aſinus, quam reſpondere</hi> Ariſtoteles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>4. <hi>When the caſe is ſo difficult that we cannot attain to clearneſs and certainty, muſt not we follow the moſt probable way?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Whether you are not upon a dangerous Point, to ſuggeſt that the caſe of Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm, is to be judged of by Probabilities and not Certainties? And if you will needs have our way of Baptiſm to be more difficult than yours, who can know it? Seeing there is thus much ſaid by a <hi>learned Man</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt your Way, viz. <hi>That there is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Dr. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>low.</note> 
                     <hi>neither Precept nor Preſident for Infant-Baptiſm in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.—That there is nothing in Dr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>or Mr.</hi> Baxter<hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:206466:17"/> 
                     <hi>about Infant-Baptiſm, that looks like an Argument.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will not be hard for any Body to ſay more for Pedo-baptiſm, and againſt our way of Baptizing Believers, than they have done? And yet whether it be not ſafe for us to ſee you offer more than <hi>your Probabilities,</hi> before we part with our Baptizing Believers, for your ſprinkling of Infants?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>5. <hi>And is it not a ſpirit of Raſhneſs, and Headineſs, that runs Men preſently upon NEW untried Ways, upon every doubting about the Old?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Whether the way of Baptizing Perſons upon perſonal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith by Immerſion, be not the old way of Baptizing, and granted to be ſo by the Learned of your own Church? for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Ludovicus Vives, Grotius,</hi> and <hi>Diodate.</hi> And then, whether you are not the raſh and heady, who run ſo eagerly after the new mode of Infant-ſprinkling? And are not thouſands involved in your new Way, before they do or can try it? And on the contrary, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any can rationally be ſuppoſed to cloſe with our Way, before they have tried it? Seeing we put all Men upon it, and have no Honours, Profits, or Pleaſures in this World (as you have) to engage them to our Way, 'tis the evidence of our Cauſe that doth it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>6. <hi>Is the overthrow of a Man's former weak Grounds, the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Truth which he held?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Is not the overthrow of your former weak Grounds for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, the overthrow of the Cauſe it ſelf, till you or ſome body elſe bring Grounds of ſufficient ſtrength to ſupport it?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>7. <hi>Is not one ſound Argument enough to prove any thing true? What if all the Text's that are brought, were put by, ſave one, is not that enough?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Have not we deſired you to produce but one ſound Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and one clear Text to prove Infant-Baptiſm true, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that ſhall ſuffice? But in ſtead of this, have you not ſent us hundreds of falſe Grounds, and many Texts abuſed in theſe and your former Queries?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>8. <hi>Are not evident Conſequences, drawn by Reaſen from Scripture, as true Proof, as the very expreſs word of the Text?—Will you allow of ſuch an Argument for Infant Baptiſm as Chriſt brought for the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection?</hi> Mat. 22. 31, 32, &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:206466:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label> Should not the Practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, outvy ſuch Conſequences (inferr'd by the moſt Learned) when the ſaid Conſequences fight againſt plain Scripture Preſidents? as <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38. <hi>to</hi> 41. <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26, 27. But who could ever prove that all Church-Members (as She contains all the ſaved, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or Heathens) muſt be Baptized? Might it not more ſtrongly be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that all Church-Members muſt be admitted by Faith, from <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26. <hi>We are all the Sons of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> Heb. 11. 6. <hi>He that cometh to God, muſt FIRST believe that God is?</hi> And how ſhall all Infants believe on him of whom they have not heard, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10? And who taught you to make Baptiſm more neceſſary to Church-Memberſhip than Faith? But why ſhould your Conſequences be made of equal Authority with Chriſt's? For he could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but you may? And why may not our Conſequences be as valuable as yours? ſpecially ſeeing ours agrees with Chriſt's own Practice, <hi>John</hi> 4. 1. as we know yours do not?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>9. <hi>Should not the former and preſent Cuſtoms of the holieſt Saints and Churches be of great weight to humble and moderate Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in Caſes controverted and beyond their reach?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Should not the undeniable Cuſtom of the firſt Churches, immediately governed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, be of more weight with humble and moderate Chriſtians, than the Cuſtom of any ſince their times? And whether your Conſcience do not tell you we follow the Cuſtom of the firſt Churches? Alſo whether there hath not very holy Men in many Ages ſince Chriſt oppoſed Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as well as in theſe latter Times? Nay, is not the firſt clear men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it gathered from them that oppoſed it? Such were <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> acknowledged by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> to be for the delay of Baptiſm to Children, till they could underſtand it. And though it is alledged that <hi>Nazianzen</hi> was not againſt it in danger of Death, yet whether this be not rather againſt than for Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, ſeeing they might as ſafely die without it, as live without it? For did it in his judgment more pleaſe God, that Infants ſhould live unbaptized? How then can their dying ſo be diſpleaſing to him? Were not the Children among the <hi>Jews</hi> as much accepted who lived ſeven days Uncircumciſed, and died before the eighth day, as if they had lived till the eighth day and then have been Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? And may we not hence conclude, that ſeeing God hath not made the Age of any Perſon a Rule in the caſe of Baptiſm, as he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:206466:18"/> did in the caſe of Circumciſion, but hath made it proper to the time of the New Birth, at what time ſoever it ſhall happen; that <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen</hi> his ſuppoſed allowance of Infant-Baptiſm in danger of Death was groundleſs? But why do you arrogate <hi>the greateſt Holineſs</hi> to your Parts, which agree with you in the caſe of Infant-Baptiſm? <hi>Why holieſt Saints? Why holieſt Churches?</hi> Though I wiſh you more holy than you are, and honour what Chriſtian Vertues I ſee in any of your Party, yet let me faithfully tell you, that your Churches by means of your Pedo baptiſm, are become the unholieſt (gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally) of all the Chriſtian Churches in the World. And how can it be otherwiſe? When by this means you take in (not only thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> God and work Righteouſneſs in every Nation, but) the whole Nations themſelves, the greateſt part whereof, God knows, are very far from Holineſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>10. <hi>Is this Controverſie in it ſelf conſidered, of ſo great moment, as ſome would make it?—Why then was it not in the Creed? Doth not the Apoſtle ſpeak of Baptiſm as a ſmall part of his Work in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Preaching,</hi> &amp;c? 1 Cor. 1. 14. 17, &amp;c. Mark 16. 16. <hi>He that believeth not</hi> (not he that is not Baptized) <hi>ſhall be damned,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Whether you Pedo-baptiſts do not make this Controverſy of greater moment than any others, whilſt the greateſt number of you (to wit, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and many Prelatiſts) do teach that none (no not Infants) can be ſaved <hi>without Baptiſm; or deſire of Baptiſm?</hi> And whether you ſay any leſs, <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Query</hi> 17. when you tell us, Infants are not ſo much as <hi>ſeemingly in a ſtate of Salvation,</hi> without your Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm? And do you not then make it more Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental and abſolutely Neceſſary than the <hi>Baptiſts</hi> do? who only ſay, not the want, but the contempt of Baptiſm damneth? And what though baptiſm be not mentioned in the Creed, <hi>which you call the Apoſtles Creed,</hi> (though you never be able to make that ſaying good, <hi>according to the exactneſs of ſpeech)</hi> yet ſeeing Baptiſm is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that Summary of Chriſtian Doctrine, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1, 2. which may more certainly be called the Apoſtles Creed than that by you ſo named, doth it not thence follow that Baptiſm is neceſſary to the beginning of a Chriſtian Man? Or will you ſay that any Man can be admitted into the Chriſtian Profeſſion, to partake of the Lord's Table without Baptiſm? And what need was there to ſay, <hi>Mark</hi> 16. 16. <hi>He that is not Baptized ſhall be damned?</hi> When its to be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:206466:18"/> ſuppoſed he that believeth not, will not deſire to be Baptized? <hi>Luke</hi> 7. Neither indeed ought he to be Baptized becauſe he believeth not, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. And if all Chriſt's Commands great and ſmall are to be obeyed (as you grant) then why not this, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38 <hi>REPENT AND BE BAPTIZED EVERY ONE OF YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> And though it be true that <hi>Paul</hi> eſteemed (and that rightly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Preaching to be a greater work than Baptizing: Yet when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he hinder any for being Baptized with the Baptiſm of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as you do? Or where did he ſhew any zeal at all for Pedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm as you do? And are you not then deluded to ſpend ſo much time, in defending your own Tradition? And with what credit can you blame others (whom you conſtrain) for ſpending time to break the Snares which you have laid in the way of Sinners, to cauſe them to continue in Error.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label>J. B.</label> 
                     <q>11. <hi>Though the point of Infant-Baptiſm be comparatively of leſs mement; yet whether the grounds on which it ſtands, and which are uſually denied with it, be not of great moment?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label>T. G.</label>Whether this be not like a Contradiction? For ſeeing every Ordinance receives, from the grounds on which it ſtands, its very being, and value; How can the Ordinance be of ſmall moment, when the grounds on which it ſtands are of great moment? And how can Infant-Baptiſm ſtand upon grounds of great moment, when it is not <hi>grounded upon Scripture,</hi> nor <hi>determined by Scripture,</hi> as is confeſſed by many <hi>Pedo-baptiſts,</hi> both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and Prelatiſts?</p>
                  <div n="2" type="division">
                     <head>DIVISION. II.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Concerning the Commiſſion, Matth. 28. 19.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>Having done with your Preparatory Queries, I come now to try your <hi>Main Queſtion,</hi> and the Queries which attend upon it. Your Query is thus ſtated by you:</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>Whether ſome Infants ought not to be Baptized?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Do we not alwayes tell you of Infants in general, that <hi>they ought not to be Baptized?</hi> So that you had better ask thus, <hi>Whether ſome Infants ought to be Baptized?</hi> For ſhould you be put to ſhew, <hi>That ſome Infants ought to be Baptized,</hi> and <hi>that other ſome ought not,</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Crage</hi> was pleaſed to Fable it out at <hi>Abergavenny)</hi> it would
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:206466:19"/> prove too hard a Task, and never be done <hi>by plain Scripture proof.</hi> But I ſuppoſe I underſtand your Queſtion, I ſhall therefore follow you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>1. <hi>Ought not all Chriſt's Diſciples ordinarily to be Baptized?</hi> (Matth. 28 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>) <hi>May not the word Diſciple be taken in a larger ſence Relatively—for one that belongs to Chriſt, as well as in a narrower ſence for thoſe who are actually Learners.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Here you ſeem to grant, <hi>That ſome of Chriſt's Diſciples ought not to be Baptized (i. e.</hi> their caſe being more than ordinary) and then I would know why Infants may not be excuſed, ſith it muſt be an extraordinary thing, if any Infant be Chriſt's Diſciple? <hi>For if Infants be Diſciples, they are either made ſo by God or Man;</hi> that God does make ſome, or all, or any Infants at all, Chriſt's Diſciples, no Man can demonſtrate. And I demand whether ever Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> or your ſelf, did make an Infant Chriſt's Diſciple according to the import of the <hi>Verb</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>? And if your Conſciences ſhall tell you that you never did, or could make an Infant Chriſt's Diſciple, how can you ſuffer your ſelves to be deluded with this fancy of a <hi>Relative Diſcipleſhip? i. e.</hi> for one that belongs to Chriſt; For why may not all Infants belong to Chriſt, as well as thoſe which you ſprinkle? And then why do you not call all Infants Diſciples? Is not Chriſt the Maſter and King of all Infants, whether Men will vouchſafe to devote them to him or no? How dreadfully do you leſſen his Authority, or Soveraignty?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>Doth not the Holy Ghoſt call them Diſciples?</hi> Acts 15. 10. <hi>Is it not evident that thoſe on whoſe Necks the falſe Teachers would have put the Yoke were Diſciples? If you ſay not all but ſome of them,—then will it not follow that it is but ſome only whoſe Circumciſion the Synod doth conclude againſt?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Does not the Holy Ghoſt ſufficiently expound <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 10. not to intend Infants? Whilſt in <hi>Verſe</hi> 19. he notes them to be <hi>ſuch as from among the</hi> Gentiles <hi>were turned to God,</hi> and are not all that are called <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Ver. 10. called <hi>Brethren,</hi> Ver. 23. and as ſuch are <hi>written unto by the Aſſembly?</hi> And was not their Epiſtle read to all <hi>the multitude of the Diſciples?</hi> Ver. 30. and did not all <hi>the Diſciples rejoyce for the Conſolation?</hi> Ver. 31. And is it not ridiculous to ſay the Holy Ghoſt intends Infants? <hi>Ver.</hi> 10. and yet excludes them in the Appellation <hi>[Diſciples]</hi> in all the other places? And is it not groſly fallacious, to ſay, That becauſe the falſe Apoſtles would have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:206466:19"/> put the yoke of Circumciſion upon the Necks of the Diſciples, that therefore all were Diſciples, whom they would have Circumcis'd? Is there any more truth in it than in this? <hi>Auſtin</hi> would have Infants brought to the Lord's Table, therefore all were Infants whom <hi>Auſtin</hi> would have brought to the Lord's Table? Or is it not clear from <hi>Ver.</hi> 1. that the Diſcourſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. does only concern the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? <hi>Except ye be Circumciſed—ye cannot be ſaved;</hi> this they are ſaid to teach <hi>the Brethren,</hi> and thereby to ſubvert <hi>their Souls.</hi> And can you think the falſe Apoſtles could ſubvert the Souls of Infants? And is it not a ſad thing that you ſhould thus grope for the Wall at Noon? and deceive your ſelves and others with meer Fallacies and Ridiculoſities. And why was not the Decree, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient repeal of Circumciſion, in reſpect of Infants, ſeeing the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples themſelves were diſcharged, or freed from that Yoke? and then whether your Abſurdity concern any Body ſo much as your ſelf?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>2. <hi>If no Infants are Diſciples, what is the cauſe? Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not capable? Or is it becauſe God will not ſhew ſuch a Mercy? Can you find a third cauſe?—If Infants are capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Servants of God, how can they be thought incapable of being Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> Lev. 25. 41, 42, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Is not Inſtruction the cauſe of Diſcipleſhip, as truly as Teaching is the cauſe of Learning? And what inſtruction or teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath God appointed for Infants? and if none (as I am ſure you can aſſign none) then what cauſe have they to learn? And if no cauſe to learn, then what cauſe can they have to be Diſciples? And therefore what cauſe have you (a Learned Man) to query ſo unlearnedly? And ſhould I follow you in your Fancies, I might alſo demand, what is the cauſe that Infants are not Repentant (ſeeing they are Sinners) is it becauſe God will not ſhew them ſuch a Mercy? <hi>To-grant them repentance unto Life,</hi> what is the cauſe they have not Faith? Is it becauſe God will not ſhew them ſuch a Mercy, as <hi>to purifie their Hearts by Faith?</hi> What is the cauſe they are not brought to the Lord's Table? Is it becauſe God will not ſhew them ſuch a Mercy, as to partake of the Body and Blood of their Redeemer? Eſpecially ſeeing it is ſaid, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of God, and drink his Blood, you have no Life in you.</hi> What? Will God deny Life through Chriſt to Infants? Now if Infants want no Mercy from God though they be denied all theſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:206466:20"/> Mercies, what reaſon is there for you to cry ſo loud againſt God becauſe they are not Diſciples? And what though Infants ſhould be called God's Servants, does it follow they muſt needs be <hi>Chriſt's Diſciples,</hi> according to <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 19? Why then the <hi>Sun, Moon, and Stars, are Chriſt's Diſciples too,</hi> for they are called God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 90, 91. Rub your Eyes from the miſt they have attracted by poring upon Mr. <hi>Baxters Fables,</hi> and know, that God will ſhew all the Mercy to Infants which they have need of (as is ſhew'd before) though he give them not all the Mercies which he gives to ſome, and particularly this mercy of Diſcipleſhip, which they have no need of during Infancy, ſith they <hi>cannot diſcern between the right Hand and the left.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But you query ſtill, <hi>Whether the Infants of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>were ſo God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Servants, as the Infants of the</hi> Jews <hi>were?</hi> And do you not here fairly grant that all Infants are God's Servants, though not SO as the <hi>Jews</hi> Infants were? But you will not ſay that all Infants are Chriſt's Diſciples: And then have you not confuted your own Fancy, ſeeing it's plain from your own words that the Title of <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> does not neceſſarily infer the Title of Diſciples? And why may not God ſet more by one Servant (and ſo by one Infant) than by another, and yet love them all ſufficiently? and may not this ſatisfie your demand why God ſhould ſhould grant a Year of Jubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee to the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Infants, when he granted not that Mercy to others? Elſe what will become of all Chriſtians and their Infants? for pray, Sir, when had they ſuch a <hi>Jubilee,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed once in Fifty Years? And yet I hope we have no cauſe to murmur againſt God, as if he were not Merciful enough both to us and to our Infants.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>3. <hi>Are not Infants capable of being Subjects of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? and is not Chriſt's Church his Kingdom, and his School?—Are not all Subjects of Chriſt in his Viſible Kingdom (or Church) Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? And are not Diſciples and Chriſtians all one?—</hi>Acts 11. 26, &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>What if we grant that Infants are Subjects of Chriſt's Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Kingdom, in reſpect of his Purchaſe, common Protection, the Deſignation of them to his Service (on the part of true Chriſtians) and in reſpect of the Bleſſing of Heaven it ſelf? Yet how doth it follow hereupon that they are capable of all the Priviledges of his Viſible Kingdom? Much leſs of the Duties of his Subjects? And do you not your own ſelves exclude them during Infancy, from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:206466:20"/> all Priviledges and Duties of Religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as much as we do) except your ſuppoſed Baptiſm? And where do you find that any Infants are called Chriſtians? <hi>Certes,</hi> the Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 26. ſays no ſuch thing: I ſee no ground to call any Infant by the name of its Parents Religion, for then the <hi>Child of a Papiſt</hi> muſt be called <hi>a Papiſt,</hi> the Infant of a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> muſt be a <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> the Infant of a <hi>Quaker,</hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> &amp;c. But is not that ſaying of <hi>Tertullian</hi> more rational, <hi>We are not born</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but made Chriſtians?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J B.</label> 
                        <q>4. <hi>Whether were not ſome Infants once to be admitted Members of the Viſible Church, by the merciful Gift and Appointment of God not yet Repealed.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether Infants once admiſſion to particular Ordinances in the Church, be part of the Moral or Ceremonial Law? How could it be a part of the Moral Law, ſeeing it had no being in the World till <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time? Was not the Moral Law obſerved by the Faithful in all Ages? When yet there was no ſuch admiſſion of Infants to Ordinances in the Church? Seeing then this Admiſſion muſt be a part of the Ceremonial Law, was it not for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the merciful Gift of God, and was not the whole Ceremonial Law the ſame? And yet whether the taking away of the whole Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law was not a Mercy, and conſequently that Admiſſion of Infants by that Law, done away in Mercy alſo? And ſeeing Infants could then but belong to the Kingdom of Heaven, with that painful admiſſion by Circumciſion, is it not a greater Mercy for them to be declared by Chriſt to be the Children of God, and to belong to the Kingdom of Heaven without it? <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 10. And is not this ſpoken of little ones indefinitely, ſeeing elſe it will follow Men may deſpiſe ſome of them? but does not our Saviour include them all in this ſpeech, <hi>That which was loſt?</hi> How then can you exclude any of them, when he ſaith, <hi>He came to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>5. <hi>Were not Infants part of them that entered into Covenant with the Lord, that he might eſtabliſh them to be a People to himſelf?—</hi>Deut. 29. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, 11, 12. 13. <hi>And were not Infants engaged by the Seal of the Covenant, Circumciſion?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. was not made for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny before they were born? How then could it be a Covenant for Admiſſion of them to Viſible Church-Memberſhip? Or dare you ſay that Infants were by this Covenant obliged to any Act of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in Infancy? And how then does it ſuit your Caſe? Again,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:206466:21"/> Do you think it would be lawful, by this, or any other Law, for Chriſtians to enter into a Covenant, Oath, and a Curſe (as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did) that our Children ſhould be of our Religion? Or are your Infants bound by your Solemn League and Covenant, to be for the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> way of Religion? And what ground have we to believe that God will eſtabliſh our Children for his People, as he did promiſe to the Children of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> i. e. <hi>To be a glorious Nation above all the Nations of the Earth.</hi> Can you prove that ſuch Promiſes are made to the Chriſtian Church militant? Or doth not Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf ſometimes ſay all that need be ſaid, or can be rightly ſaid on theſe words, <hi>Ero Deus tui &amp; ſeminis?</hi> It ſufficeth (ſaith he) that God will be to them a God of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>Friend Accom.</hi> p. 361.</note> and do for them all that is neceſſary, to put them <hi>in ſtatum ſalutis, pro conditione parvulorum.</hi> And we demand whether God did not thus much for all Infants in the firſt Edition of the Covenant of Grace, which he confeſſes, <hi>is not Vain, nor Repealed by God.</hi> Did he not do all that was neceſſary (to put them into a ſtate of Salvation) for the condition of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones?</p>
                     <p>If Infants were engaged by Circumciſion (as you here obſerve) then they were not Viſible Church-Members without it. And then doth it not plainly follow, that Circumciſion being Repealed, this their Viſible Church-Memberſhip is Repealed alſo? Or will you ſay they remained in <hi>Viſible Church-Memberſhip without an Ordinance?</hi> and ſo deſtroy your <hi>Maſter-piece,</hi> in one Member of it? And let that Typical Memberſhip be accounted (as it was) <hi>a merciful Gift,</hi> yet when the Antitype made that Type null, it was a great mercy that it ceaſed; nor ſhall we fail of proof in this caſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16, 17. <hi>cum multis aliis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>6. <hi>Dare any of you ſay that God hath Repealed Infants Church-Memberſhip to their hurt in Juſtice?—Or can you ſay it is in Mercy for their good? How can it be a Mercy to take away a Mercy, except it be to give a greater Mercy in ſtead of it?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Though we might ſay much of the Juſtice of God in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing the Covenant of Circumciſion, and therewith the Infant Church-Memberſhip once allowed in the Jewiſh Church, yet how dare you ſay that this was to the hurt of any Perſon, whether In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant or any other? But we will abide by this, that God made this Repeal in Mercy. And how ſhould you not ſee, that to be ſet at
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:206466:21"/> Liberty from the Yoke of the Law, and from Circumciſion, which made them Debtors to the whole Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 3. was all done in mercy? And was it not needful to abrogate the firſt, or old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that he might eſtabliſh the new or ſecond Covenant? <hi>In which though we have no particular order to admit Infants to the Duties of this Covenant,</hi> yet we are ſufficiently recompenſed, in the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance given us by Chriſt concerning <hi>Infants right to the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> and his <hi>bleſſing them,</hi> without Baptizing them; that ſo, they are as happy whilſt Infants, as we can deſire they ſhould be: And is not this a greater Mercy than the Old Covenant did give to any Infant by Circumciſion? As for the Capacity of thoſe who are concerned in the Duties of the Second Covenant, is it not expreſly thus: That the <hi>Law of Chriſt ſhould be put in their Hearts,</hi> and <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their Minds,</hi> Heb. 8. And, <hi>So God to be their God, and they to be his People,</hi> as <hi>knowing him,</hi> from the <hi>leaſt of them</hi> to the <hi>greateſt?</hi> And whether in theſe reſpects any Infant can from Truth or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be ſaid to be in the New Covenant? And how then are they to be admitted Members of this Viſible Company or Church, ſeeing they know not God? And yet is it not very evident, that the Grace of the New Covenant extends to them, from our Saviour's Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Again, Was not Infants partaking of the Paſſover, and other Sacrifices and Rites of the Law, as great Mercies as their being circumciſed? And yet what Mercies of this kind was given them in the taking away of theſe? and yet were they not all taken away in Mercy? And whilſt you deceitfully lay the ſtreſs of the word Mercy, upon your Sprinkling of Infants, do you not invalidate the ſubſtance of thoſe Types, which being come, for the Salvation of Infants (as well as others) is their ſufficient Paſſover, though they cannot celebrate the memorial of it in Bread and Wine, as the Adult ought; and do? And is not the <hi>true Jubilee which came by Chriſt,</hi> a ſufficient Gain in ſtead of the <hi>Jewiſh Jubilee,</hi> both to the Adult and to Infants, though neither the one nor the other hath any <hi>Jubilee</hi> in the nature of an Ordinance in ſtead thereof? Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially not Infants, ſeeing they know not the ſound of the Goſpel.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>7. <hi>And is there any Scripture that ſpeaketh of delivering any from this ſad eſtate</hi> (meaning to be without hope) <hi>but Church-Members?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:206466:22"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label> Will <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 12. prove that no Infants among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were ſaved? Does not that Scripture, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14, 15, 26, 27. as clearly prove that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> which had not the Law, and yet did by Nature fulfil the Righteouſneſs of the Law, ſhall be as much excuſed in the Day of Judgment as the <hi>Jews</hi> who kept the Law? And do you not here eſpouſe that Doctrine, <hi>Out of the Church is no Salvation?</hi> Not <hi>conſidering that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Body of Chriſt may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend many that had never the opportunity to be incorporated into the Viſible Company of ſuch as worſhip God in the uſe of Legal, or Goſpel Inſtitutions.</hi> And will you thus damn all Infants in the World but thoſe that are Sprinkled, or Croſſed by the Pedo-baptiſts? And will not the Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 47. <hi>alleged by you,</hi> if compared with <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 14. make againſt you? Seeing thoſe that <hi>were added to the Church,</hi> were not Infants, but <hi>Men and Women?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>8. <hi>If it be no benefit to the Catholick Church to have Infants kept out of Heaven, nor hurt to the Church to ſee them there, why ſhould it be a benefit to the whole Church to have them kept out on Earth?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>If I might follow your Fancy, I might ask you what hurt it will be to the Church, to ſee an Infant of a poor <hi>Indian</hi> in Heaven? And why then do not you admit them here on Earth? But is it not childiſh in you to ſuppoſe that any ſhall be Infants when in Heaven? Seeing, according to <hi>Auſtin,</hi> they are called Infants <hi>A non fando,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot ſpeak; may we not more rationally believe that what is loſt of ſtature, and knowledg by the Sin of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſhall be reſtor'd by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt? And are not Infants as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſeen in the Aſſemblies of the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> as in yours? And do we not devote them to God in our Prayers as well as you? And what do your Infants partake of (except your Tradition of Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them) which ours do not as fully enjoy? And is it not as great a benefit to the Church to delay the Baptiſm of their little ones, as to delay their coming to the Lord's Table? If your delay make them more fit for the one, does not ours make them more fit for the other? If ours die without the one, do not yours die without the other? What cauſe then of your murmuring? For who caſts In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants out of the Church? Is not this a <hi>Barbariſm?</hi> For if they be in, we do all we are allowed of God to keep them there, by timely Inſtruction, and by imploring God's Bleſſing for them, and you do no more, <hi>only you Croſs, or Sprinkle them?</hi> This is your all, on this you build your hope for your dying Infants. This your <hi>Tradition</hi> is therefore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:206466:22"/> your <hi>Idol.</hi> This is that ſmall parcel of bad Wooll, about which you make this hideous Cry, as if God had no Mercy for poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants unleſs this be done; <hi>Why are you ſo Imprudent?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="division">
                     <head>DIVISION III.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>Concerning Rom. 11. 17.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>1. <hi>Is it not evident from</hi> Rom. 11. 17. <hi>That only ſome of the Branches were broken off from the Church? Therefore the reſt remained in, the Gift was not Repealed. Doth not the Apoſtle ſay it of that Church whereof Infants were Members?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Here you ſeem to hold that the Church in her Legal ſtate, and in her Evangelical ſtate were both one, in <hi>ſuch a ſenſe,</hi> as that <hi>he that by Faith was added to the Chriſtian Church,</hi> was <hi>not broken off from the Jewiſh Church. Hence I Query,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Does not <hi>Paul</hi> plainly ſhew, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 1. <hi>to</hi> 8. That the Chriſtian Church was freed from the Law of her former Husband? When therefore ſhe ceaſed to be a Wife, upon the account of the Law, did ſhe not then ceaſe to be a Church on that account, that ſhe might now be married to another, even to Chriſt, and ſo bring forth Fruit unto God? Why then ſhould theſe words <hi>[ſome were broken off]</hi> be underſtood, to ſuppoſe that ſome yet did ſtand by God's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment <hi>in the former Church?</hi> Or, is it not evident, that Mens <hi>eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſtand in the Old Church</hi> (which now was ceaſed <hi>de jure)</hi> was the <hi>cauſe why they were rejected?</hi> Again, Is it not ſaid of the believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> That they were grafted in among the Branches (to wit, the <hi>Jews)?</hi> ſure this is <hi>not meant of the Jews, that ſtood in the Houſe of</hi> Moſes, or <hi>the Old Church-ſtate;</hi> but of the Church or Houſe which was builded by Chriſt: for <hi>Old things were paſſed away, all things became New.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wherefore now conſider, ſeeing the believing <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves did not ſtand by virtue of their Old Church-Memberſhip, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now Repealed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 4, 5, 6. whether it be rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal to imagin that the Infant Church-Memberſhip (which was of the ſame Law) ſhould yet remain? And wherefore do you ſo boldly ſay, the believing Parents do remain <hi>in the ſame Church?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But further, Is it ſafe by the <hi>good Olive,</hi> Rom. 11. to underſtand
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:206466:23"/> the Jewiſh Church? Was not <hi>Paul</hi> willingly broke off from that Church, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. that he might be in Chriſt? Is it not more ſafe to underſtand the place, of <hi>Abraham not as a Natural Father,</hi> for ſo the <hi>Gentiles</hi> could no more be grafted into him than into the Jewiſh Church; <hi>But as a Spiritual Father,</hi> into whom as ſuch the Faithful were grafted, or rather <hi>into his Seed, in whom all Nations ſhould be bleſſed,</hi> even Chriſt, the true Vine? and the Faithful, both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> are the Branches united to him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>2. <hi>Is it not evident from</hi> Rom. 11. 20. <hi>That none of the</hi> Jews <hi>were broken off, but for unbelief?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>And is there any thing more clears the Point, that this breaking off was not from the Jewiſh Church? for their unbelief cauſed them to ſtand in that Church? And ſeeing theſe two things are both evident, that the breaking off here meant, was by unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and the ſtanding here meant, is by Faith; is it not thence very evident that the poor Infants are not concern'd, either in this kind of breaking off, or this kind of ſtanding in the Olive Tree? <hi>Alas, poor Souls, what have they done?</hi> Have not Infants a more ſure intereſt in Chriſt, than to be jetted into, or out of him, by the Faith or Unbelief of Parents? What wiſe Man will think ſo? And what need have we, or any Body elſe, to talk of the Inviſible Church, it being a thing unknown to Man? And <hi>ſuppoſe this Olive Tree be meant of the Viſible Church Chriſtian,</hi> walking in all the Commands and Ordinances of Chriſt blameleſs; yet ſeeing no Natural Branches (as ſuch) do ſtand in this Olive Tree, but muſt be grafted in by Faith, before they can ſtand there; Is it not evident, even hence, that no Infant, meerly as the Seed of a Believer, is concern'd in the Duties of this Church, ſeeing the very Natural Branches of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, have not that priviledg on that account?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>3. <hi>If it be into their own Olive Tree (which they were broke off from, and of which they were Natural Branches) that the</hi> Jews <hi>ſhall be engrafted at their recovery (as</hi> Rom. 11. 24.) <hi>then how is God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Infant Church-Memberſhip Repealed,</hi> &amp;c.<hi>—though they be not reſtored to the Moſaical Law, or Covenant of Peculiarity, but taken into the Catholick Church?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Though it be never ſo true that the <hi>Jews</hi> upon their return ſhall be grafted into their own Olive, <hi>viz. Abraham,</hi> as a Spiritual Father, and into Chriſt the Promiſed Seed, in whom all Nations are bleſſed; yet do you not here fairly grant that they ſhall not be grafted
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:206466:23"/> into the Covenant of Peculiarity, or Moſaical Law? And then whether their bringing Infants to the Myſteries of Religion (which was one main thing which was peculiar to the Jewiſh ſtate) is not conſequently granted by you to be now Repealed, unleſs you can prove that the Catholick Church hath Command from Chriſt to bring their Infants to the Myſteries of Religion? And who (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>your ſelves) did ever exclude the <hi>Jews</hi> Infants from the Catholick Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the Aſſembly that are written in Heaven? But how will you prove that the Infants of the <hi>Jews,</hi> or any dying Infants, are caſt out of that Church? Or, are not all thoſe of the Catholick Church, who are of the Kingdom of God? And does not Chriſt ſtate Infants there without excepting any?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>4. <hi>Is it not the ſame Olive or Church, which the</hi> Jews <hi>were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off from, that we</hi> Gentiles <hi>are grafted into, as</hi> Rom. 11. 17, 19, 24? <hi>And if theirs admitted Infants—muſt not ours admit of Infant-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers alſo?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether the Church was not the ſame Church in all Ages? and yet whether ſhe did not differ in her external order by God's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment? and whether this difference was not in the caſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants being brought to, or left unconcern'd in the Rituals of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as much as in any thing? And ſeeing you here ſay, <hi>She was taken down as to accidental Ceremonies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> whether this will not juſtifie us in not Baptizing Infants, as well as you in not Communicating them, ſeeing God hath not commanded the one any more than the other?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>5. <hi>Would not Chriſt have gathered</hi> Jeruſalem?<hi>—And is it likely that he would have unchurched all their Infants, when he would have gathered to him whole</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>or the whole Nation?</hi> Matth. 25. 37, 38, 39.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether it be not evident we unchurch no Infants, in reſpect of their relation to Salvation by Chriſt, but only ſay they ought not to be brought to the Services of Goſpel-Ordinances? And do not you your ſelf ſay the ſame that we do, except your pretended Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? And ſuppoſe Chriſt had gathered all <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> would not he have gathered them after the ſame manner? Would he not have gathered them by Preaching, by Repentance, and by Faith and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, which were capable of theſe things? But how ſhould their Infants be thus gathered? Could he not have gathered their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants (in the ſende of this Text) without Preaching to them,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:206466:24"/> without Faith or Repentance, required of them? And could, and would he not have gathered them without Baptiſm, as well as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe? And ſhould not the Infants in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judea</hi> have eſcaped the deſtruction which came upon them by the <hi>Romans,</hi> if the Adult had but received the Goſpel? and can you think that though the Infants ſuffered in that Deſolation of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that therefore they were damned with the unbelieving <hi>Jews?</hi> And if not, were they not ſtill of the Catholick Church, though their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were rejected?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>6. <hi>Can you ſuppoſe the believing Jews Children (and ſo the Parents in point of Comfort) to be in a worſe condition ſince Chriſt than they were before?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Was not <hi>Enoch, Seth,</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> (when Infants) as happy though not Circumciſed, or brought to any Ritual in the Church, as <hi>Iſaac, Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. were in their Infancy, though Circumciſed? And have we not as much ground to believe our Infants as happy (though not Baptized) as any Infant of the Faithful in the Old World? And did not <hi>Auguſtine</hi> think Infants as miſerable if they died without the Lord's Supper, as you think them to be if they die without being Croſſed or Sprinkled? And yet do not you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he was deceived? And are we not as juſtifiable to believe that you are alſo deceived? Is it not as needful to feed upon Chriſt in the holy Supper, as to put on Chriſt in holy Baptiſm? Can you have comfort concerning your Infants in the want of the one, and muſt we have none concerning our Infants in the want of the other? And what is now become of the Covenant of Grace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. if Infants can have no benefit by it, but on the condition of their Parents works of bringing them into the Church by your Tradition, as you ſuggeſt in the latter part of this Query?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>7. <hi>If the Church be not in a worſe ſtate now—will it not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that our Children ougbt to be admitted Church-Members?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this be not a falſe ſuggeſtion which keeps com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with moſt of your Queries; <hi>viz.</hi> That all Infants which are not brought to ſome Rite or Ceremony, are put out of the Church? Were the Infants of ſix days old in <hi>Iſrael</hi> put out of the Church? Did not thouſands of Infants die before they were admitted to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion? And if they were in the Church before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it were lawful to Circumciſe them, why may not ours be in the Church, as well as the Infants of ſix days old in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> before and until it be lawful
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:206466:24"/> to Baptize them? May we not do well to <hi>nurture</hi> and fit them for Baptiſm, as they <hi>nurſed</hi> and fitted them for Circumciſion? And what though our Work may require more Years than they theirs did Days; yet we making all the ſpeed that God requires, are we not as excuſable as they? And what though ſome of our Children die before they can be fitted for Baptiſm? Did not ſome of theirs die before they could be fitted for Circumciſion? And why may not we have comfort in our diſappointments by Death, as well as they when ſo diſappointed? And ſuppoſe our Children refuſe to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized when they come to underſtanding, and will not be fitted for it by all that we can do? what comfort would it be to have had them Sprinkled in their Infancy, when now we find them reject Faith and Repentance, the moſt ſubſtantial parts of true Baptiſm?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>9. <hi>If the Children of Believers now be put out of the Church, are they not in a worſe condition than the very Children of the</hi> Gentiles <hi>were before the coming of Chriſt?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Do you not abuſe the World to talk at this rate, as if either God, or we put Infants out of the Church, when the only Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is about their admiſſion to ſuch or ſuch Duties of Religion? Wherein yet you do the ſame, <hi>in many caſes</hi> (as I have ſhewed) which we do in the <hi>caſe of Baptiſm.</hi> And if any have in the heats of Diſputation, <hi>abſolutely denied Infants to be of the Church,</hi> yet you know their ſence is <hi>only to deny your way of making them Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:</hi> Not but that they all aſſert Infants to be of the Body of Chriſt, of the number of the ſaved, and ſo of the Church. <hi>And I here aſſert they are of the Viſible Church, becauſe by the Word of God, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be accepted of God, to the Grace of Life through Chriſt.</hi> But we put no Infants out of the Church. For example, <hi>I have had many Children (for which I give thanks to God): as ſoon as he gives them to me, I do by Prayer to God devote, and heartily commit them to him; and by his Grace I do my beſt to teach them the Knowledg and Fear of God, as they grow up; and (I bleſs God with this ſucceſs) that all that yet are capable, have been Baptized. And now wherein am I to be charged for putting my Children out of the Church? And if I be Innocent (as I know I am in this) then I hope the Churches of the ſame Faith are as excuſable.</hi> And whether, if there were faithful Miniſters of Chriſt in every Pariſh, it might not be a more likely way to bring Souls to true Chriſtianity, to inſtruct the Children twice or thrice a Week (eſpecially ſuch Children whoſe Parents cannot inſtruct them) as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:206466:25"/> ſoon as they could learn, and ſo to fit them for Baptiſm; than to run to the Miniſter with them to be Baptized in their Infancy, when God knows, neither the Infants, Prieſts, nor their Parents, know what they do?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>9. <hi>Was not the Covenant,</hi> Deut. 29. 10, 11, 12.<hi>—a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace as diſtinct from the Law which was Repealed? How then is it, or Infants Church-Memberſhip, grounded on it, Repealed?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Seeing this Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. obliged the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to the whole Law, and left them under the Curſe of the Law if they kept it not as appears by reading <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. and <hi>30th Chapters;</hi> will it not follow that all the parts of this Covenant was not of the Covenant of Grace? Indeed ſome things repeated, or expreſſed here, might pertain to the Covenant of Grace. But what then? Why Infants Church-Memberſhip, ſay you, is grounded upon it. And I pray, who denies that by the Covenant of Grace Infants are Members of Chriſt, of his Body, or the Univerſal Church? But what then? muſt they therefore be brought to the Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Church, viſibly profeſſing the Worſhip of God, in all Ages, as much as in any Age? This indeed is your falſe Inference, and with this you delude your ſelf and others. And how long will it be, ere you make the Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. and 30. agree with that which you quote out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. in all Points? And if they differ in any thing, why may it not be in this, the one admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Infants to Circumciſion, and other Rites of the Law; the other only brings thoſe that know the Lord by the word of Faith, being in their Heart and Mouth, to partake of Inſtitutions of the Goſpel?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>10. <hi>If Infants then were entered—Members by that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, which was a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith;—How comes that Church-Memberſhip to be Repealed?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Not to contend with you whether Circumciſion was a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith to any that had not the Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> (though plain Truth, and all good Reaſon ſeems to be full againſt you) yet to conceſs a little to ſee the moſt you can ſay, how do you prove that none were Church-Members before they were Circumciſed? And how was <hi>Abraham</hi> admitted a Member of the Church by Circumciſion? Was he not a Member of the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Circumciſed? Was not <hi>Iſaac</hi> a Member of the Church before he was eight Days old? Were they not Circumciſed becauſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:206466:25"/> God had taken them into a Church-Covenant, rather than to enter them into a Church-Covenant? And is it not therefore ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 14. That ſuch Men children as were not Circumciſed, ſhould be cut off from his People, becauſe they had broken the Covenant? And is it not plain then that theſe Children were already in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and of the Church? elſe they could not be cut off. And yet whether any thing here threatned, concern the Eternal State of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants? Shall we think that God would damn them to Hell, becauſe their Parents neglected to Circumciſe them? Or is it like a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace to make ſuch a Ceremony ſo abſolutely neceſſary to the Salvation of Infants? Now ſeeing Infants were not made Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church (much leſs of Heaven) by Circumciſion, what need we aſſert the Repeal of their Memberſhip in the Church (as it contains the whole People of God) but the Repeal of Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion is evident, and there-withal they are freed from any Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Duties of Religion, unleſs it can be ſhewed that God hath appointed the contrary, which never yet could be ſhewed. Thus if we give you all the advantage imaginable, yet nothing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crues to your Cauſe from this inſtance of Circumciſion, till you can ſhew Authority from God to Baptize Infants, as plain as they had to Circumciſe Infants: For does not one of your own Way tell us, <hi>That Circumciſion is a fine Hiſtorical Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mr.</hi> Brooks.</note> 
                        <hi>to illuſtrate a Point well proved before; but is not this that wherein you always fail? i. e.</hi> to prove by plain Scripture what you promiſed?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>11. <hi>If the Law of Infant Church-Memberſhip, was no part of the Ceremonial, or meerly Judicial Law, nor yet of the Law of Works, how can you ſay it is Repealed, ſeeing no other Laws are Repealed?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether theſe words <hi>[The Law of Infant Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip]</hi> be a lawful Speech? And by what Law will you make it good? But (not to contend about words) if by <hi>Law,</hi> you mean the Covenant of Grace made with lapſed <hi>Adam,</hi> Gen. 3. 15. Then whether we do not aſſert it to be in force, more fully than you do? But if you mean any other Covenant ſave this, (for the often repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of it makes it not another Covenant): then we ſay, it is your duty to aſſign or ſhew that Law, or Covenant; and we will conſider it, mean while take notice, <hi>That for the Repeal of that temporary Order once uſed to admit Infants to Ceremonies in Religion, is ſhewed (and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally granted) to be repealed in the Repeal of Circumciſion, and no Inſtitution</hi>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:206466:26"/> 
                        <hi>or Ceremony (ſince the Repeal) ordained for Infants; and this is the Point in queſtion.</hi> Why then go you about to <hi>wheedle</hi> us with a noiſe of words, of <hi>a Law of Infant Church-Memberſhip unrepealed? A Law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>unrepealed?</hi> And whether you or Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> either, can in the ſight of your own Conſciences ſay, that you well underſtand what you ſay?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And here I ſhall advertiſe the Reader, that as the remainder of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries we are to reckon with, are leſs ſpecious than theſe we have examined, ſo let it be remembred, That we have granted, and do now once more aſſert, that by virtue of the Covenant of Grace made with fallen</hi> Adam, <hi>and all Mankind in him, Infants ſtand in a ſtate of Grace, publiſhed (by God himſelf) to Man, ſo that they are viſibly in a ſtate of Salvation; nor will God break this Covenant, it is unalterable, for he is faithful. Infants do not tranſgreſs againſt it, therefore they ſtand in this Covenant. This Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was and is the Church-Covenant n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>w confirmed by Chriſt, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Witneſs of it: And by this Covenant Infants are Members of his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, his Body, that ſhall be ſaved. In the time of the Law when this Covenant was much Vailed, or hid under Shadows,</hi> Rom. 16. 25, 26. <hi>God was pleaſed to admit Infants to ſundry of the Carnal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Law; but now the Myſtery of the Goſpel being diſplayed to all Nations, and the Worſhip of the Goſpel being heightned to a very Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Nature. God hath not engaged Infants in theſe Services, as he did in the time of the Law. Our Adverſary thinks otherwiſe; this is our Difference: try ſeriouſly, and judg righteouſly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="division">
                     <head>DIVISION. IV.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>About Infants viſible Church-Memberſhip.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>1. <hi>Is it not clear that there is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal viſible Church, and that every one that is a Member of a particular Church, is alſo a Member of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal? And that the</hi> Jews <hi>Infants were Members of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, and that this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal is not diſſolved? Now muſt not he that will affirm, the whole ſpecies of Infants are caſt out of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal viſible Church, prove it well?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this Query be not grounded on meer Fancies? for though they that are Members of a particular Church, are Members of the Univerſal Church; yet dare you ſay, or think, that none are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:206466:26"/> Members of the Univerſal, which are not alſo Members of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church? Is not this the Dream with which you are Infatuated, to hold the Damnation of all Infants, yea, of all Perſons who are not Members of ſome particular Church? And where do you find that Infants are caſt out of the Univerſal Church, if they are not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized? is the Univerſal Church no larger than the Number of the Baptized? Can you think that the Uncircumciſed Infant was caſt out of the Univerſal Church? Suppoſe they were neglected till the <hi>10th, 20th,</hi> or <hi>40th</hi> day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will you imagine them to be the Subjects of the Devil? What ſtrange conceits have you of God? It's true, the Uncircumciſed were cut off from the particular Society of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but did that Society conſtitute the Univerſal Church? Were none (what not an Infant in all the World) in a viſible ſtate of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except thoſe in that Society? Me-thinks <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſhould teach you to think otherwiſe. And what is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Covenant of Grace, if Infants be ſo liable to be caſt out of the Univerſal Church as you ſuggeſt? But why do you call the Univerſal Church Viſible? Is not this a viſible Miſtake? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the latter part of this Query be pertinent, unleſs it be againſt your ſelf? For if the removal of Perſons, whether Infants or others, out of a particular Church, be no found Argument that they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the Univerſal Church: then ſeeing the viſible Profeſſors of the Truth in this World, are but a part (and perhaps no very great part) of the Univerſal Church, may not Infants remain in the Univerſal Church, though not incorporated, or imbedied with any particular Church practizing the Ordinances of God?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>2. <hi>Is not that falſe Doctrine which makes the Children of the Faithful to be in as bad, or a worſe condition than the Curſe,</hi> Deut. 28. 32, 41. <hi>doth make the Children of Covenant-breakers to be in?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Is not this an injurious ſurmiſe? As if none were bleſſed in the Fruit of their Body but you, whoſe Infants are Croſſed or Sprinkled? But who puts Infants out of the whole Viſible Church? Do we not maintain the Church-Memberſhip of Infants as far as Scripture will bear it? Firſt, By the Covenant of Grace made with all Mankind, and now confirmed by Chriſt by whom they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and pronounced to be of the Kingdom of God. 2. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law or Covenant of Circumciſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> during the term of the Law, till Faith came, or till the time of Reformation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>3. <hi>Doth not the Doctrine which puts Infants out of the Viſible</hi>
                           <pb n="52" facs="tcp:206466:27"/> 
                           <hi>Church of Chriſt, leave them in the viſible Kingdom of the Devil?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Is not this a Diabolical ſurmiſe? Are any Infants of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Kingdom of the Devil? Are your Infants of the viſible King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Devil till you Sprinkle them? Did not Chriſt declare them to be of the Kingdom of God, when yet not one Infant that we read of was Baptized? And what if your Croſſing or Sprinkling prove no true Baptiſm, will it not follow from this your injurious Doctrine, that all your Infants are of the Kingdom of the Devil? Are any of the viſible Kingdom of the Devil till they ſubmit to his Deluſions? and can you charge Infants with this? Be aſhamed, O ye <hi>Presbyterians!</hi> of this.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>4. <hi>And will you leave us no ſound grounded hope of the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Salvation, of any dying Infants in the World?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Is not this Query a meer fooliſh out-cry? How plainly do you here damn all Infants that are not Sprinkled? Is not this the only cauſe of all this Clamour? What Doctrine can be more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous than this?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>5. <hi>What a full plain Text is that,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 14. <hi>Are the Children of Believers holy in ſtate? then ought they not to be admitted viſible Church-Members?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>How fully and plainly does <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 2. explain this place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. Is not Marriage honourable among all Men, and the Marriage-bed undefiled? And is not that which is undefiled holy in ſtate? And is not the unbeliever ſanctified in this ſtate, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14? Ye who but Men willing to be deceived, will ſay they ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be Baptized? And are not the Children therefore ſaid to be holy, becauſe the Unbeliever is ſanctified to, or by the Believer? And how then can that Holineſs be any other than Matrimonial? And does not <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his <hi>Paraphraſe,</hi> give this very expoſition on this Text? And does not <hi>Auſtin</hi> tell you, That whatſoever this Holineſs is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. yet <hi>it is not of power to make Chriſtians, or remit Sins?</hi> And why do you grudg that all Infants, procreated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Ordinance, ſhould be holy? See <hi>Malachi</hi> 2. 15. Doth not <hi>Diodate</hi> on the Text ſay plainly, <hi>That God's chief end in this proceeding,</hi> [to wit, in ordaining Marriage] <hi>was, that the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity might be Sanctified, being born in chaſte Wedlock according to his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, whereas it is defiled by all manner of unlawful Conjunctions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>6. <hi>When it is ſaid,</hi> Mark 10. 14. Of ſuch is the Kingdom of God, <hi>Whether this be not more, than they may be viſible Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:206466:27"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label> Whether we do not readily conſent to all that is ſaid <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 14. concerning Infants? do we not grant they are viſibly ſtated in a gracious Right to the Kingdom of God? And if this be more than to ſay, Let them come to Baptiſm; Is it not more alſo than to ſay, Let them come to the Lord's Table? And is it not very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, that though three Evangeliſts mention theſe Infants, yet none of them ſo much as hints that they were Baptized? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſe words, <hi>ſuffer them to come to me,</hi> will not be a better plea for us in the Day of Judgment, in devoting our Infants to God by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Name of Chriſt, than for you, in going ſo much beyond the Text, as to Croſs or Sprinkle them, without the leaſt ground from this, or any place of Scripture? And whether this your preſumption, be not the real cauſe of our differences in Religion?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="division">
                     <head>DIVISION V.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>About the Texts objected againſt the Pedo-baptiſts.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>1. <hi>If theſe Texts,</hi> Rom. 9. 8.—Epheſ. 2. 3. <hi>be objected. To the firſt Text: What is it the Apoſtle mainly drives at, but that Men are not therefore ſaved becauſe they are</hi> Abraham's <hi>carnal Seed?—And to</hi> Epheſ. 2. 3. <hi>What though we are by Nature Children of Wrath, doth it follow that we may not be otherwiſe by Grace?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Seeing you here grant that Men (but you muſt mean In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants alſo) are not ſaved becauſe they are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Natural Seed, and that you diſpute not the certainty of their Salvation, but only their Church-Memberſhip; Have you not meerly trifled all this while? Seeing now here is no ſound ground it ſeems from their Church-Memberſhip to prove them ſaved? And ſeeing none, as they are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed according to the Fleſh, are either ſaved, or Members of the Church, ſo as to partake of Ordinances, is it not ſtrange that you ſhould prefer your Carnal Seed before his?</p>
                     <p>But how are Infants Children of Wrath in the ſence of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 3. otherwiſe than with reſpect to that Condemnation which came by <hi>Adam?</hi> And is not that made void by Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5? We readily therefore conſent, that Infants are otherwiſe by Grace.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>2. <hi>If you object that Infants are not capable of the ends of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: To this, though Infants are not capable of every benefit of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,—yet</hi>
                           <pb n="54" facs="tcp:206466:28"/> 
                           <hi>are they not capable of the principal ends? May it not be a Liſting Sign?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Here you grant that Infants are not capable of every bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Baptiſm, nor can you prove them capable of all the benefits which you aſſign: For how are Infants capable of receiving Baptiſm as a Liſting Sign? Ought there not to be a free conſent on the part of him that is Liſted? Or do you not rather preſs poor Infants (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their will, as appears by their reſiſting you what they can) then truly Liſt them? Or how do they engage to be God's People, or take Chriſt to be their Lord (as you feign)? are not theſe meer Flouriſhes, and confuted by all Experience? And do not you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute your ſelf, when you tell us here that <hi>they underſtand none of theſe things?</hi> And what benefit of Baptiſm are Infants capable of, more than they are capable of the benefits of the Lord's Table? If Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sin be held forth in the one, is it not held forth in the other? And will you narrow up Remiſſion of Sin to your way of Baptiſm? And muſt we ſtill be ordered by Bonds and Leaſes to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Goſpel Myſteries? Do you think to prevail by theſe Fancies?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>3. <hi>And may it not be Operative by its ſignification as ſoon as the Child comes to the uſe of Reaſon? And in the mean time, as his Intereſt is, upon the condition of the Parents Faith,—ſo may not the Parent have the actual comfort of it,—as of a Leaſe that aſſureth an Eſtate to his Child?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>It ſeems then Baptiſm operates not by its ſignification, till the Child comes to Reaſon, and you will not ſay it operates by the Work wrought? Why then cannot you let the Child ſtay till he have the uſe of Reaſon? And is it not abſurd in you to ſay, that your Sprinkling aſſures the Parent of Heaven for his Infant, as a Leaſe aſſures him of an Eſtate? And why then did you tell us it was not the certainty of Salvation which you diſputed for? What ſtrange comfort do you give Parents concerning their Infants? Would any Parent value ſuch a Leaſe as only names his Child, but gives no certain right to the Inheritance? Nay, for ought he knows, the Eſtate is more certain to one that is not named in the Leaſe <hi>(for that's the true Import of your holding ſome dying Infants are damned):</hi> but what a wretched Intereſt do you give the Child, whilſt it reſts upon the condition of the Father's Faith? Poor Child! if thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Faith be falſe (as many are corrupt in that caſe) or if he fall from the Faith (as many do) what is then become of thy Intereſt?
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:206466:28"/> May not you, as <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> before you be truly called, <hi>Durus Pater Infantium?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You ſuggeſt as if the Child's Baptiſm will operate as ſoon as it comes to the uſe of Reaſon; but that is falſe by all Experience: he muſt have better means than your Sprinkling, or he ſhall never be a Chriſtian. You urge the <hi>Sinleſsneſs of Chriſt.</hi> But ſuppoſe your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were as Sinleſs as he, would that intitle them to Baptiſm? I dare ſay you would hold it an Argument to the contrary. And what though <hi>Chriſt was not buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm?</hi> Yet is that a Warrant for you to Baptize thoſe that cannot be buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm? And whether would your Fancies lead us at laſt, ſhould we admit your Argumentation in other Caſes?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>4. <hi>If you object, How can an Infant covenant with God, or be engaged by this Sign?—To this, if only the Aged are capable of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, may you not thence conclude that no Infant was ever circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? But may not that be the Childs action Morally, or in a Law-ſence, which is only the Fathers action Phyſically? As when a Man puts his Childs name into a Leaſe?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether you do not here grant the circumciſed Child did not covenant with God properly but in a Law-ſence? And do we not grant this becauſe there was a Law for it? There was alſo once a Law <hi>for the Circumciſion of Trees,</hi> Lev. 19. 23. <hi>[Take away his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin, which is his Fruit.</hi> Ital. Tranſl.] Now ſhew us your Law for your Mode of admitting Members, <hi>viz.</hi> Sprinkling of Infants, and we will diſpute no farther. And would you not count us very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if we ſhould Baptize our Trees, becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> did Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe theirs? And then why may not we count you as unwiſe to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize Infants, becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> did Circumciſe Infants? But what Book of God taught you this fine diſtinction, <hi>viz.</hi> That my Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm muſt be <hi>anothers act Phyſically,</hi> and <hi>mine Morally?</hi> And let this Fancy run, and what Ordinance can you deny an Infant which his Father may perform <hi>Phyſically? i. e.</hi> As he may put his Childs name into a Leaſe, which is the thing you refer us to, to underſtand your diſtinction by.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>5. <hi>Another common Objection is, If Infants muſt be Baptized, why may they not as well receive the Lord's Supper? To which, may not the very external nature of the Sacraments ſatisfie you?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Why do you not ſee your Error? Does not Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> tell you, <hi>The Wit of Man is not able to ſhew (in this caſe) a difference in</hi>
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:206466:29"/> 
                        <hi>theſe Ordinances?</hi> And are not little Children as capable to receive a ſmall quantity of Bread and Wine, as to be Baptized? And did not Men admit them to both for five or ſix hundred Years together? Does not the Apoſtle ſay of the whole Church who were engaged in the Chriſtian Worſhip, <hi>We are one Body and one Bread, even as we all partakers of that one Bread?</hi> 1 Cor. 10. And might not any Man argue as ſtrongly from hence for Infant Communion, as you from any other Text for Infant Baptiſm? And does not God's requiring Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of every one that is to be Baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37, 38. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain Baptiſm to ſuch, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. reſtrains the Supper to ſuch as examine themſelves? And does not your Inſtance of a Burgeſs-Infant make againſt you, whilſt you confeſs he is not born to Trade on his Infancy? Why then ſhould Infants Trade in the Myſteries of the Goſpel, though born to the Grace of Life, held forth to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in the Goſpel?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>6. <hi>It bath been objected, That if it be the will of God that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants ſhould be Baptized, it is ſtrange that he hath left it ſo dark? To which, will you not grant that all Church-Members muſt be admitted by Baptiſm?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Dare you ſay that all that are under the benefit of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace muſt be Baptized? And yet are not all ſuch of the Univerſal Church? Are none of the Infants of the <hi>Jews</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; and yet you will ſay they muſt be Baptized? Is it not as plain that all Church-Members muſt eat and drink at the Lord's Table, as that they are all to be Baptized? Does not Chriſt ſay, <hi>Drink ye all this?</hi> Does not <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>We being many, are one Body,—for we are all partakers of that Bread?</hi> Let Infants then be never ſo truly of the Church, as ſhe contains the whole Body of Chriſt, yet are they not of that Body which are bound to put on Chriſt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and to <hi>continue ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine, in breaking of Bread and Prayers.</hi> And whether the remainder of this Query hath not been conſidered before?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>7. <hi>Another Objection is, The evil conſequences of Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, as groſs Ignorance much occaſioned by it. To which,</hi> 1. <hi>Is not the Lord Jeſus himſelf the occaſion of the ruine and damnation of Multitudes?</hi> Luke 2. 34. 2. <hi>Can you ſhew what there is in the nature of the thing that ſhould be hurtful to any?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Is not that of very evil Conſequence, that <hi>naturally tends,</hi> to deprive <hi>all Men</hi> of the <hi>ſacerd Ordinance of God,</hi> the <hi>Baptiſm of</hi>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:206466:29"/> 
                        <hi>Repentance for the Remiſſion of Sin?</hi> Can you deviſe any way <hi>ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> to fill the Church with Unregenerated Perſons? And is not this a great evil, when God hath ordained the <hi>New Birth,</hi> as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to <hi>Memberſhip in his Goſpel-Church?</hi> Do you not evidently turn things upſide down? And contradict our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 3. 3, 5. and his Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 26. And is not this evil? Is it not evil to ſpeak a word in the Name of the Lord which he never commanded? How dare you then ſay, you Baptize an Infant in the Name of the Lord, when you cannot but know you ſpeak falſly in his Name; and can ſhew no Authority from Heaven for Baptizing Infants, if you did the thing indeed? Suppoſe any ſhould bring Infants to the Lord's Table, what evil can you ſhew us <hi>in the nature of the thing,</hi> that we cannot as well ſhew you in the <hi>nature of your Croſſing or Sprinkling?</hi> And how dare you crack it up to be more ſolemn, than our way of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Repenting Believers? Do we deny any to be preſent when we Baptize, that are fit to be preſent? And why do you count the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of Chriſt and his Flock immodeſt, in compariſon of your own Tradition? But more of your Immodeſty anon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>
                           <hi>If God would have Infants to be Church-Members, and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by Baptiſm, are not all theſe Objections againſt God, and a Carping at his Way?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this be not an idle Query? And ſeeing it does not appear that it is the Will of God that Infants ſhould be admitted to the Church profeſſing the Goſpel, by Baptiſm; are not you evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Men that carp at the People of God, and complain becauſe Men will not lay aſide the Command of God, and obſerve your Fancies and Traditions?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="division">
                     <head>DIVISION VI.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>About deferring or delaying Infant-Baptiſm.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>1. <hi>Where do you find one word of Precept or Example in all the Bible, for the deferring the Baptiſm of any Child of a Chriſtian till years of Diſcretion? Should you not bring ſome Scripture for your Way?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether it be not vain in you to talk of our delaying Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, when we take the firſt tender of any Perſon (unleſs we have juſt cauſe to the contrary) to diſpence that ſacred Ordinance? Does
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:206466:30"/> not DELAY ſuppoſe a preſent capacity and obligation for Duty, and then to put it off? But what Scripture have you to Baptize Members of the Church, and then to delay their other Duties and Privileges for 15 or 16 Years? And what Precept or Example have you to Baptize Perſons when they are aſleep? (As your Infants of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten are when you Sprinkle them) And who taught you to Baptize Perſons <hi>per force,</hi> whether they will or no? As that is your common practice: As is confeſſed, when we are told by <hi>Auſtin, That Infants do ſtrive againſt Baptiſm with great Crying.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>2. <hi>Is not your Way inconſiſtent with obedience to the Rule? Is it not Chriſt's Rule that Perſons ſhall be Baptized without delay when they are firſt made Diſciples? Doth not this appear,</hi> Mat. 28. 19, 20.<hi>—How can you Baptize (any) when they are firſt made Diſciples<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unleſs it be in their Infancy?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Why do you not come forth, and make ſome one Infant (at leaſt) a Diſciple, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19? Would not ſuch a thing, done by you, do more to decide this Controverſy, than a thouſand Queries? I require you to come to the Teſt here, or elſe may we not juſtly count you vain Talkers, and eſpecially you of the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> who whilſt you boaſt more of making Infants Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples than other Pedo-baptiſts, yet you do no more than they, that is juſt nothing? And why do you ſuggeſt that we cannot tell when a Perſon is firſt made a Diſciple? Did the Apoſtles know this or not? And why may not others know this as well as they? Seeing they judged not in this caſe by immediate Revelation, but by Perſons glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiving their Doctrine, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 40, 41. And how can you tell when an Infant is firſt made a Diſciple? Are you not aſhamed to pretend to know with eaſe, what is not to be known at all, that ſo you might make all Men ignorant of that they ought to know?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>3. <hi>Would not this Practice of yours neceſſarily fill the Church with perpetual Contentions, as being about a Matter that cannot be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by any known Rule?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>May I not be confident, that it is hard for any Man to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry more indiſcretly than he that formed this Query? But, Sir, we are ſure your Practice hath filled the World with Contention, both in former and latter Ages: your Biſhops could not agree on what Day to Baptize Infants, you cannot tell us the Day. He that ſhould not be Baptized, <hi>till you Miniſters agree this Point,</hi> by one Voice, ſhould he ever be Baptized? As for us, we have a known Rule to walk by,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:206466:30"/> and that is, to Baptize them the ſame day they are Converted, if they reject it not. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 41. <hi>Then they that gladly received the Word were Baptized; and the ſame day was added unto them about three thouſand Souls.</hi> Yet it may be thought that the noble <hi>Bereans</hi> were longer about it, becauſe <hi>they ſearched the Scriptures daily, to ſee whether things were ſo.</hi> Yet who (but ſuch as feed on Fancies) would imagine the time when they were to be Baptized, could not be determined by any known Rule? And why? Forſooth, becauſe they came gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually to the knowledg of the Truth, <hi>ſpectatum admiſſi,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>4. <hi>When you pretend to ground your practice on</hi> Mat. 28. 19, 20.<hi>—would not your Doctrine turn Baptiſm (for moſt part) out of the Churches of the Saints? For according to you, only they that are made Diſciples by Miniſterial Teaching, directly ſhould be Baptized,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this your talk of directly, indirectly, and remotely diſcipling the Seed in the Parent, be not plain Barbariſms rather than the Simplicity of the Goſpel? And that cunning Craftineſs whereby you deceive your Admirers? And whether ſuch your indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect doings have not turned holy Baptiſm for the moſt part out of the World? But do you not err, to ſuggeſt that we would have none made Diſciples, but by immediate Miniſterial Inſtruction? Does not <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19, 20. ſhew that Miniſters are to teach thoſe whom they have diſcipled, to obſerve the things which Chriſt commanded his Apoſtles? and is there not liberty ſufficient here for every one to ſpread the knowledg of the Goſpel as he is able, in his Family, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, as God gives him opportunity? And is it not a great ſhame that you ſhould thus forge an Opinion to be ours which we never owned, and then to quibble upon it as you do? I profeſs I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to reade you in this, and many of theſe your imprudent Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; which I cannot perceive to have any deſign but to throw ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Blocks in the way of Chriſtians generally, and to make <hi>them queſtion almoſt every</hi> thing.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="division">
                     <head>DIVISION VII.</head>
                     <argument>
                        <p>About the manner of Baptizing.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>1. <hi>Your ordinary practice of Baptizing by Dipping over Head in cold Water (which you uſe as neceſſary) is it not a breach of the Sixth Commandment,</hi> Thou ſhalt not kill? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:206466:31"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label> Is not this Query blaſphemous? In that it <hi>reproacheth the Footſteps of God's Anointed?</hi> Was not Chriſt Baptized of <hi>John into Jordan?</hi> (So the <hi>Greek</hi> reads it) Was not that cold Water? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was <hi>Baptized in the Winter ſeaſon;</hi> for he was born about Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winter, and Baptized when <hi>he began to be about thirty Years of Age,</hi> muſt it not then be about the ſame time of <hi>Winter?</hi> Is there <hi>any Form</hi> of Baptiſm neceſſary? Or hath God left that to you, <hi>to invent what Form you will?</hi> May we not better follow <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Form</hi> than yours? Did not Chriſt know rightly how to be Baptized? Will not your Way admit of as many Forms of Baptiſm, as there are parts in a Mans Body? And ſhould any urge the ſame part to be the fitteſt part to be Baptized, which was formerly Circumciſed, might not a Man that would ſtrain his Wits and Conſcience, give as probable Arguments for that, as you do for the ſubject of Baptiſm, whilſt you reaſon from Circumciſion? Do you not boldly out-face the Holy Ghoſt by your Sprinkling, <hi>John</hi> 3. where he tells us the Reaſon why <hi>John</hi> Baptized in <hi>Eanon,</hi> was, becauſe there <hi>was much Water?</hi> And why went <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> both down into the Water, if your Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Sprinkling were a due Form of Baptizing? Does not <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date</hi> (and many of your Learned Men) tell us, that <hi>(Rom.</hi> 6. 4.) <hi>Baptiſm was a Dipping in Water; according to the ancient Ceremony?</hi> Were the ancient Chriſtians Murtherers? When will you bluſh at your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate Vanities? Nay, do not you grant that Dipping was the uſe of the Church in Scripture-times, only you ask us <hi>whether it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly uſed?</hi> But if you lay inconſtancy to their Charge, ſhould you not prove it? Does your Inſtance of the Jaylor prove it? Or do not you ſhew that you reade that place with blind Eyes? Elſe you will find they <hi>went out of his Houſe</hi> even at <hi>Midnight,</hi> to celebrate holy <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> for is it not plainly ſaid, That when he and all his were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, <hi>that he brought them into his Houſe, and ſet Meat before them?</hi> And yet, had they not been in his Houſe before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>to Preach to him and to all that were in his Houſe?</hi> And can any place be more full againſt your childiſh Sprinkling? And whether Mr. <hi>Fiſher<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> and Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> hath not ſufficiently anſwered your frivolous Quibbles about the quantity of Bread and Wine in the holy Table? And alſo your Quirk about warm Water to Baptize in? And ſeeing by the courſe of Providence Water is warm in the <hi>Summer,</hi> in compariſon of what it is in <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> how ſhould it be a Sin to Baptize in warm Water? And that God which ordain'd Water for our nouriſhment as Men, allows us to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:206466:31"/> uſe it warm or cold, as may be moſt healthful and convenient. And why ſhould we think it unlawful to uſe it ſo in the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm if neceſſity require it, as in an extreme Froſt perhaps it may? And ſo in reſpect of the weakneſs of the Subject, is here any change of the Ordinance? And will not <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 7. <hi>I will have Mercy and not Sacrifice,</hi> better defend ſuch an innocent Practice, than your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                           <desc>•••••</desc>
                        </gap>ion of the Ordinance?</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>2. <hi>Is it not a breach of the Seventh Commandment.</hi> Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery, <hi>to Dip Perſons naked, or next to naked?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Is not this alſo a fooliſh and blaſphemous Query? Is not the having one Garment on only next to naked? And yet may it not be decent enough to be Baptized in one Garment? But why do you ſo baſely ſuggeſt that it is our practice to Baptize naked? Is not our conſtant Practice known to be otherwiſe? Are not both Men and Women attired in decent Garments among us when Baptized? Why do you thus ungraciouſly Scandalize an Innocent People? Will you not ceaſe to pervert the right Ways of the Lord; And to make his Ordinance contemptible as your Fellows did, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 6. 7? Yea, this Reproach hath been by your means, <hi>O ye Prieſts;</hi> And let me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to lay it to Heart. And are you not more perverſe ſtill in the remainder of your Query? As if <hi>the Dipping Perſons cloathed, would deſtroy our Argument for waſhing the whole Body?</hi> What is this? You grant Dipping was uſed in the Scripture-times, ſure they were Dipped either with Clothes, or without them: And is it not ſaid of them that their <hi>Hearts were ſprinkled from an evil Conſcience, and their Bodies waſhed with pure Water,</hi> Heb. 10. 22. Now what ſhall we ſay to your <hi>ungodly Query?</hi> It will not permit us to be Baptized by Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping (as you grant it was uſed in Scripture-times) neither with Clothes nor without. So then, nothing but your Croſſing or Sprinkling can pleaſe you. How true is the Proverb? Some <hi>Men are much in love with their own Fancies.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>3. <hi>What fruit of theſe things? How many of you that inſtead of labouring after the winning of Souls from Sin to God, make it your main ſcope to propagate your Opinion?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this Query be not Hypocritical? As if the buſineſs of your Hundreds of Queries did not ſpeak you to be as fond of your Opinion as any other? Or as if the winning Souls from the Errors wherein you have entangled them, and by which you have hardned them againſt plain Truth, were not a winning Souls to God? And
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:206466:32"/> have not you compelled us to defend what we hold? And do you now blame us for ſpending time to unmask your Falacies? For my own part, I could have been glad to have forborn this Labour: But what did you publiſh your Queries for? Was it that you might bear it high againſt the Truth, and that no Man ſhould examine them? And is not your intolerable Calumnies againſt what we profeſs, and your immoderate ſtickling for Pedo-rantiſm, the cauſe of thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions (at leaſt in part) which you would charge us with? As for Prayer in Families, if there be no ſinful Impoſitions and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, which of us are Enemies to Family Devotions? And are not you as ſtrait in this as other Men? Would you have more Unity with us? This you pretend. But then ceaſe your Heats for things really diſputable, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> confeſſes Infant-Baptiſm to be: <hi>Yea,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I know it to be a very difficult Point,—</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>B.</hi> Def. Prin. Lo. p. 7</note> 
                        <hi>and many Prelatiſts have maintained that it is not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in Scripture.</hi> You may be ſure therefore, you ſhall not hector us into your Opinion, by calling us Murtherers and Adulterers, meerly becauſe of our Baptiſm. And who that is wiſe would take ſuch courſes for Union with Diſſenting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? Sure this will keep us from your Communion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>4. <hi>Whether it be at all credible that Satan would be ſo charitable to Believers Infants, as to plead for their Priviledges, or would be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagater of Chriſt's Kingdom?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Wretched Charity! Is this Charity to damn hundreds of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, that you may plead for one? Was not <hi>Auguſtine</hi> as Charitable in pleading for Infants Communion, as you are in pleading for their Baptiſm? Were not the falſe Apoſtles (in their own Opinion) as Charitable as the beſt of you all for Infants, when they would have had them Circumciſed? For ſay they, except ye be Circumciſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ye cannot be ſaved. And ſay you leſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Infants be Baptized (as they were Circumciſed under the Law) there is no ſound ground of Hope concerning any dying Infant in the World? But in good earneſt, whether we or you, be really and indeed the moſt charitable to Infants, let him that reades theſe Books impartially, judg? And how your practice of Pedo-baptiſm hath propagated Chriſt's Kingdom, may be ſadly ſeen among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> where yet Pedo-baptiſm is more common than with you? And how his Kingly Government is oppoſed by your withſtanding his Counſel againſt your ſelves, is too evident. Men have a knack to pretend
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:206466:32"/> Chriſt's Kingdom, when it is their own that they ſtrive to ſet up: and 'twill be well if you do it ignorantly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>5. <hi>Whereas we tell Sinners of the heinous aggravation of their Sins, as committed after Baptiſm,—Whether you that make Infant-Baptiſm a Nullity, dare undertake to bear the burthen of that Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them?</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether you deceive them not in telling them they are Baptized, when they are not? Yet how dare you charge us for going about to extenuate any Sin, at any time, more than your ſelves? And whether does not Mr. <hi>B.</hi> himſelf make Infant-Baptiſm a Nullity? When he ſaith to the Adult (notwithſtanding their Infant-Baptiſm) <hi>They were never ſtrictly</hi> nor <hi>comfortably in Covenant with Chriſt,</hi> till they <hi>freely conſent;</hi> and (ſaith he) <hi>it was never a match till now.</hi> And then is not this the fit time to Seal the Covenant (as you ſpeak); for he ſaith, <hi>their Infant-Covenant will not now ſerve.</hi> Saints <hi>Everlaſting Reſt,</hi> P. 178, 182.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label>J. B.</label> 
                        <q>6. <hi>Whether it ſhould not lie heavy on tender Conſciences, to add to God's Word, holding the Repeal of the Ordinance of Infant Church-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip?—How doleful is it that any Chriſtians ſhould be ſo zealous to diſpute their Children out of Chriſt's Church,—and whether they may not have as many thanks from Chriſt, as the Diſciples had for keeping ſuch from him?</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label>T. G.</label>Whether this be not the great evil of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> to add to God's Word, telling the World he has given plain Scripture-proof for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm, when in truth there is not one word for their being admitted Church-Members by Baptiſm? And whether we do not ſufficiently evince, that we diſpute no Infant out of the Church of Chriſt, though we deny them to be admitted by Baptiſm? And wherein the Chriſtian Man's Infants have a bleſſing in the timely Dedication of them to God (as far as the Chriſtian hath allowance from Chriſt, to bring them to him) which others have not who are born of thoſe that know not God, have we not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhewed in our firſt Book, and now alſo in this? And whether (for all this Noiſe) Mr. <hi>B.</hi> does not make Infant Church-Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a meer Trifle, <hi>unleſs they be ſprinkled,</hi> when <hi>that's all the cauſe</hi> of the Cry, that <hi>they have no ſound grounded hope concerning them;</hi> and that <hi>for this cauſe</hi> they are ſuppoſed to <hi>be left in the Kingdom of the Devil?</hi> And whether Chriſt will give Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> more thanks for THUS diſputing unbaptized Infants <hi>out of Heaven,</hi> than he gave to <hi>Auſtin</hi>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:206466:33"/> for diſputing Infants out of <hi>Life Eternal,</hi> becauſe <hi>they were not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated with at the Lord's? Table.</hi> And whether it be not a good wiſh that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> may ſee his Miſtake in the former, as 'tis ſuppoſed (by ſome) that <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaw his Miſtake in the latter?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                     <p>FOraſmuch as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (and from him Mr. <hi>J. B.)</hi> have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a very modeſt Propoſal, for more Concord among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans who differ about the Point of Infant-Baptiſm, by which it ſeems to me, that notwithſtanding the ſeverity of their Queries, and their ſtiffneſs in fighting for the Point of Infant-Baptiſm, with ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentneſs; yet this is more to let us ſee what (they conceive) <hi>may be ſaid,</hi> then what they believe, <hi>is neceſſary to be ſaid in that caſe.</hi> I will therefore ſet down the ſaid Propoſal, and intreat all my Friends that differ from them, in the Point in Controverſie, to take it into conſideration, being loth at preſent to give an Anſwer to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a matter of moment, and common concern.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="proposal">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> B<hi>'s. Propoſal.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THat if you would be contented your ſelves to ſatisfie your own Conſciences to be Rebaptized, as one that doubted whether he were well Married, would ſecure it by being Married over again <hi>[or as one that doubted his Ordination, would be Ordain'd again]</hi> and would afterwards live peaceably in Communion with your Brethren, and not appropriate Church-Communion to your own Sect: And if you would not deny our Infants Church-Memberſhip, and only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Baptiſmal Inveſtiture, for the more ſolemn Inauguration and Obligation: Though I ſhould not be of your mind, I would live in as loving forbearance and Communion with you, as with other Chriſtians.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:206466:33"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
